<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An additional appendix to the book entituled Rusticus ad academicos, or, The country correcting the clergy ... by S. Fisher.</title>
            <title>Rusticus ad academicos. Appendix</title>
            <author>Fisher, Samuel, 1605-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39565</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12900898</idno>
  <idno type="VID">95242</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240855652</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5416</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12900898</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 982:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An additional appendix to the book entituled Rusticus ad academicos, or, The country correcting the clergy ... by S. Fisher.</title>
                  <title>Rusticus ad academicos. Appendix</title>
                  <author>Fisher, Samuel, 1605-1665.</author>
                  <author>Fisher, Samuel, 1605-1665. Rusticus ad academicos, or, The country correcting the clergy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95242:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95242:1"/>
            <p>AN <hi>ADDITIONALL APPENDIX</hi> To the Book Entituled <hi>Rusticus</hi> ad <hi>Academicos;</hi> OR, The <hi>Country</hi> correcting the <hi>Clergy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN</hi> In somewhat a smaller Compasse, and closer Circumference then that of the Volume it alludes to, some few of those <hi>Rabbinical Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,</hi> which yet are <hi>obvious</hi> enough in the other, to any <hi>observant Reader,</hi> are <hi>rendred</hi> more <hi>conspicuous</hi> to the <hi>observation</hi> of all; To the end that all that have Eyes may see, and a Heart may understand, How the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>School-men</hi> are <hi>unskild</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> How the <hi>Sun</hi> is set upon the <hi>Seers,</hi> How it's night to the <hi>Diviners</hi> that they cannot <hi>divine;</hi> How <hi>the Vision of all</hi> is become unto them as a <hi>Book sealed;</hi> How <hi>blindnesse</hi> has befallen the <hi>Babel-Builders;</hi> How the <hi>Race</hi> of the (once <hi>Reverenced</hi> and <hi>Renowned) Rabbies</hi> is wrap't up in <hi>Rounds,</hi> in their (so much respected) <hi>writings</hi> against the <hi>Light;</hi> How the <hi>Doctors</hi> are doting on a <hi>Divinity</hi> of their <hi>own;</hi> The <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> and <hi>Text men</hi> tangled in their own <hi>talkings</hi> about their <hi>Text,</hi> and the <hi>Priests</hi> pull'd down by themselves in their own <hi>Prate</hi> pretensively <hi>for</hi> i. e. <hi>Pro Scripturis</hi> but in very deed <hi>against</hi> both the very <hi>Text,</hi> and the very <hi>Truth</hi> it talks on; How among the <hi>Gameliels</hi> in general, but more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly among those four choice ones <hi>T. Danson, J. Owen, R. Baxter, J. Tombs,</hi> (who, as <hi>Representatives</hi> of the <hi>rest,</hi> whose <hi>sense</hi> they speak, and in whose behalfe they reason, are <hi>reckoned</hi> with in the <hi>bigger Book</hi> abovesaid) (<hi>Ishma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>-like Every mans hand is against every man, and each mans hand against himselfe, <hi>R. B. I. T.</hi> sometimes confuting <hi>I. O</hi> and T. D. and these foure <hi>sometimes</hi> confounding and contradicting each man himself; and in a word <hi>dancing</hi> the <hi>Rounds</hi> together in the <hi>dark, tracing</hi> too and fro, <hi>crossing</hi> and <hi>cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up</hi> &amp; <hi>down, in</hi> &amp; <hi>out,</hi> and sometimes <hi>round about,</hi> in the <hi>Wood</hi> of their own <hi>wonted wisdom,</hi> in the <hi>clouds</hi> of their <hi>self-created confusion</hi> about sundry <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> they concurre in together (<hi>by the ears</hi>) against the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Contradictionibus <hi>scatet</hi> Spiritus Enthusiasticus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ʋnusquis{que} afflatum habet, ita foedè et apertè inter se a spiritu immundo commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur ut vix duo eorum in eadem doctrinâ conveniant; sed mirè digladiantes adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sas et contrarias sententias quotidie venditant, etiam in Nomine Dei se aliquotiès mutuò devovent et execrantur, Ita{que}</hi> Nihil Certi <hi>ab i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> expectare licet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Enthusiastical spirit</hi> flows with <hi>Contradictions;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So fowlly &amp; apparently are they whifled by the <hi>evil spirit</hi> among themselves, that scarce two of them can agree in one Doctrine, but clashing wonderfully, they daily vent opposite and contrary opinions, &amp; often they even curse one another in the name of God, therefore there's <hi>nothing certain</hi> to be expected from them;</p>
               <bibl>Quoth <hi>John Owen,</hi> Exer: 3. Sect: 34.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quid rides</hi> (O sacerdos? <hi>de te fabula narratur.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Homine Domini,</hi> ac in <hi>Nomine Domini</hi> (saith the Proverb) <hi>Incipit Omne malum.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>S. Fisher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilson,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95242:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN</hi> ADDITIONALL APPENDIX, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat <hi>flood</hi> of <hi>Follies</hi> and Absurdities, that <hi>Cloud</hi> of <hi>Confusions</hi> and self-<hi>Contradictions,</hi> which diffuses and shatters it self up and down by plats in <hi>sundry showers</hi> thorowout the <hi>sun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry Pages</hi> of these four mens <hi>Books,</hi> Every eye that reads them (as they lye at a distance in theirs, and in mine, by which theirs is more largely answered) may possibly not set <hi>sight</hi> on them easily: Therefore I shall cull some few of them only out (for the whole number passes my skill to cast account of) and clap them a little closer together; Not so much to <hi>shame</hi> them as to <hi>honour</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> which they would <hi>shame;</hi> That they may be the more <hi>ready</hi> to be <hi>read,</hi> and apparent to the view of every <hi>ordinary Reader;</hi> That any (save such as seeing will not see) may see the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Lord already laid on the <hi>Arm</hi> and <hi>Right-eye</hi> of the <hi>Idol-Shepheard;</hi> To the <hi>drying</hi> up of the one and the <hi>darkning</hi> of the other; For perverting the right way of the Lord, so that he not only seeth not the <hi>Sun</hi> of Righteousnesse, which he loves not that it should shine (as <hi>Elimas</hi> of old did not, for his seeking to <hi>turn</hi> away the Governor <hi>from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Faith,</hi> Acts 13. 10, 11, 13.) nor yet the <hi>Moon</hi> of so much as common <hi>sense</hi> and <hi>reason,</hi> but <hi>groaps about</hi> with him in the <hi>mist</hi> of his own <hi>muddy mind,</hi> so as to need some to lead him by the hand, and to shew him (in answer to his Question <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) whereabouts he is, and what a <hi>shaking, sandy ground</hi> he stands on.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Self-Contradictions, Confusions, and Rounds about Justification.</head>
               <p n="1">I. As to the <hi>Doctrine of Justification by Christ and his Righteousnesse with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us.</hi> 1. They tell us <hi>one while,</hi> that <hi>the 3. Question debated on</hi> at <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and <hi>held in the affirmative by the Quakers,</hi> was <hi>stated in these terms.</hi> Whether [<hi>Our] Good works</hi> are the meritorious cause of <hi>Our</hi> Iustification? which is a Lye with a <hi>witness,</hi> witnesse <hi>T. D.</hi> who tells it, P. 14. of his first Pamphlet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles (to go round again</hi>) leaving out the Term [<hi>Our</hi>] which quite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the state of the Question, and makes it altogether another, This Truth is told us; viz: <hi>That the Terms of the 3. Question were, Whether</hi> Good works be <hi>the meritorious cause of our Justification?</hi> which was expressely affirmed by the Qua: <hi>Witnesse Hen: Oxenden John Boys</hi> Esquires; <hi>Mr. Nath: Barry, Mr. Thomas Seyliard, Mr. Char; Nicolls Ministers, a few (of very many) Witnesses</hi> (quoth <hi>T. D.</hi> in his Epist: to the Reader) <hi>of the Terms of the Questions agreed to by the Qua: who will free me</hi> (and how well they free him let all the world judge) <hi>from the suspition of a partial Relator;</hi> Witnesse also <hi>T. D.</hi> himself, who (if it be the same <hi>T. D.</hi> (as no doubt it is) who wrote both that <hi>Book</hi> and the <hi>Epistle,</hi> and <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> thereto annexed) in p. 58. of the self-same Book to the <hi>Contradicting</hi> and <hi>Confounding</hi> of himselfe in the former Tale, together with those his own Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, tells all that Truth that is last related.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They tell us <hi>one while</hi> (that is, when we not only assert it, but evince it from the Rule of contraries) that its rank <hi>Popery</hi> to say, <hi>Good works</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve Iustification.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95242:2"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles</hi> (that is, when to the contradiction of themselves, they assert and evince the same from the same Rule) then (<hi>to go round again</hi>) it's no Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; Witnesse <hi>T. D.</hi> who in p. 14. of his 1. Pamphlet, sayes <hi>S. F.</hi> shews himself a <hi>rank Papist indeed,</hi> in so arguing, yet p. 15. (in proof of himselfe to be a good <hi>Protestant,</hi> &amp; no <hi>Papist</hi>) allows himself so to argue; viz: <hi>Evill works, which are the violation of the Law, deserve damnation;</hi> Ergo <hi>Good works which are the fulfilling of the Law, deserve salvation</hi> [adding] <hi>That he knows no good works such, but Christs;</hi> To which I answer, <hi>Nor do I know any good works such, but Christs;</hi> [and I adde] I own all <hi>Good works</hi> such, that are <hi>Christs</hi> and there <hi>T. D.</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents, in not owning all <hi>Christs own Good works</hi> such, but some only (namely such as he did at <hi>Jerusalem</hi>) and some, even of <hi>Christs own Good works</hi> (as namely, all such as he works in his Saints, <hi>who works all their good works in them</hi> Isa; 26. 12.) as no better then <hi>dung, losse, and filthy rags;</hi> Witnesse his <hi>blind blending</hi> of these two distinct businesses into one and the same; viz: The <hi>righteousnesse</hi> wrought by men <hi>without Christ;</hi> and the <hi>righteousnesse</hi> wrought <hi>in men by Christ;</hi> or <hi>Our good works,</hi> alias <hi>Mans own righteousnesse</hi> wrought only by men in their <hi>own wills, wisdome strength,</hi> according to their <hi>thoughts, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, conceits, traditions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>without Christs Light and Spirit</hi> (which is that only the Spirit calls <hi>Ours,</hi> that is <hi>as an unclaan thing, as filthy rags▪</hi> Isa: 64. 4. which God (speaking to <hi>Israel,</hi> that being <hi>ignorant of Gods righteousnesse, went about to establish their own,</hi> Rom: 10. 3.) calls <hi>Thy righteousnesse thy works, which cannot profit nor deliver;</hi> Isa: 57. 12, 13. And which <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 3. 9. stiles <hi>his own righteousnesse which was of the Law,</hi> as in opposition to that of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi>) And <hi>those good works of Christ</hi> in our persons, in performing whereof, the righteousnesse of the Law is said (though by <hi>Christs Power only</hi>) to be fulfilled <hi>is us,</hi> Rom: 8. 4. Or that <hi>righteousnesse</hi> which is, though in the Saints, yet of God alone through their faith in Christ Iesus the Light, Phil: 3. 9. For these two <hi>Righteousnesses,</hi> the one whereof who is not blind may see to be only <hi>mans own,</hi> which is worse then naught, and avails not, The other only <hi>Christs own,</hi> which must be of <hi>infinite worth,</hi> and <hi>des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt</hi> to justifie (as <hi>T. D.</hi> also to the <hi>further confounding</hi> of himselfe, truly consesses; p. 15. 1. Pam:) <hi>from the dignity of the person or subject</hi> (i. e. <hi>Christ</hi> in us) by whom it's performed, <hi>T. D. confounds</hi> together, both into <hi>one and the self same,</hi> and consequently concludes himself <hi>unavoidably</hi> to be (<hi>respectively</hi>) both a <hi>Self Contradictor,</hi> and (which is worse) a most <hi>abominable Blasphemer▪</hi> For if the <hi>Righteousnesse</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> that is by <hi>Christs Power</hi> performed in his Saints <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> be both <hi>Christs own,</hi> and yet <hi>mans own also.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Yet <hi>T. D.</hi> most strenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously stands to it, that so it is P. 22. 1. Pam. say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Apostle</hi> by his own <hi>Righteousnesse un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstands his personal conformity to the Law; Do you think that the righteousness Paul calls his</hi> own <hi>was not</hi> Christs?</note> Then (being one and the same <hi>individual</hi> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse) it must have a <hi>mutual</hi> participiation of the same <hi>Properties</hi> and <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ominations, respectively,</hi> so that if <hi>Christs own righteousnesse</hi> may be said to be of <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>desert</hi> to <hi>Salvation</hi> (as it truly is by <hi>T. D.</hi> himselfe the <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mans, Pauls, the Saints own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse (which</hi> T. D. sayes was <hi>Christs, received from Christ, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ought by Christ</hi>) must be consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>meritorius</hi> also, and that's a piece of <hi>rank Popery,</hi> and <hi>wretched Foppery</hi> of <hi>T. Ds.</hi> own broaching who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95242:3"/> yet would <hi>Father</hi> it upon the <hi>Qua:</hi>) which the <hi>Qua:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Had he any righteousness which he had not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? That righteousness which was in</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stle <hi>was wrought in him by</hi> Christ, <hi>as an efficient cause.</hi>
                  </note> (who own all <hi>mans own righteousnesse</hi> to be (as the Scripture sayes of it) <hi>unclean, dung, losse,</hi> and <hi>filthy rags,</hi> and <hi>utterly unprofitable</hi>) do as utterly abhorre, and so <hi>T. D.</hi> makes himselfe a <hi>Merit Monger,</hi> with a witnesse, such as never yet was found among the <hi>Qua:</hi> That <hi>dying-Qua:</hi> at <hi>Dover</hi> himself, whom <hi>T. D.</hi> belyes in that particular, not excepted.</p>
               <p>And again, If <hi>Mans, Pauls,</hi> the <hi>Saints own righteousnesse,</hi> may be said (as it truly is, <hi>Isa:</hi> 57. 12, 13. (64. 4. Phil. 3. 8.) to be <hi>unprofitable, unclean, dung, losse and filthy rags,</hi> then the <hi>self same</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> and other <hi>Saints</hi> (their own <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse</hi> being no other then <hi>Christs;</hi> then what <hi>they receive from him, and he works in them</hi> (as <hi>T. D.</hi> sayes) for their <hi>Sanctification</hi>) some of <hi>Christs own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse,</hi> Yea even that too which serves for the <hi>Saints sanctification,</hi> and to make the Saints <hi>meet</hi> for that <hi>possession,</hi> where no <hi>unclean</hi> thing must enter, <note n="*" place="margin">For are <hi>there not two righteousnesses</hi> [of Christ?] quoth he p. 22.) and <hi>they serve for two different ends; The one for our justication</hi> (meaning that which was inhaerent in that single person of old at <hi>Jerusalem) This gives us a right to the inheritance of the Saints in Light; The other for our sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> (meaning that he works in his Saints) <hi>this</hi> (though filthyrags) [mark] <hi>makes us meet for the possession.</hi>
                  </note> must be <hi>unprofitable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, dung, losse and filthy rags,</hi> which is no lesse then <hi>point blank blasphemy:</hi> yea in expresse terms, p. 23. <hi>I deny our justification by Christ in us</hi> quoth he) <hi>by that righteousnesse</hi> in us whereof <hi>Christ is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor;</hi> as if that <hi>Christ in us,</hi> and that righteousnesse of his <hi>in us,</hi> which is the same with that <hi>without us,</hi> deserved nothing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Moreover in saying there are two <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of Christ,</hi> when as the <hi>Righteousness of Christ</hi> (whether <hi>in himself,</hi> or <hi>in his Saints</hi>) is but <hi>one,</hi> he crouds <hi>confusion</hi> upon <hi>confusion,</hi> in the eye of every clear <hi>considerer</hi> of his <hi>inconsiderable</hi> stuff; which cannot but see that what God <hi>joyns</hi> together <hi>as one,</hi> this he <hi>separates</hi> and puts asunder; what is <hi>truly one,</hi> and <hi>undivided</hi> (as <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>his Righteousnesse</hi> is) this he <hi>divides,</hi> and <hi>distinguishes</hi> into two <hi>righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses; 2 Things meant by that one name of Christ, his Person and his Operations</hi> in us; The <hi>latter▪</hi> whereof <hi>he denys for righteousness to justification:</hi> But what things are <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly two,</hi> and ought accordtngly to be, and by the Lord are <hi>divided, separated</hi> and <hi>put asunder</hi> as <hi>Mans, Pauls</hi> the <hi>Jewes own righteousnesse,</hi> and <hi>that righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse which is of God by faith in Christ, received from,</hi> and <hi>wrought by Christ</hi> in his Saints, which the Scripture Rom: 10 Phil. 3. opposes and speaks of as in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradistinction each to other) These two <hi>T. D.</hi> and his <hi>Brother Builders</hi> whose <hi>work</hi> it is to build <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>confusion,</hi> as their <hi>reward</hi> is the <hi>division</hi> of their tongues) <hi>confound</hi> and <hi>jumble</hi> both together into <hi>one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They tell us <hi>one while</hi> that truth Christ tells his Disciples, <hi>Matth. 5. That except our righteousnesse exceed that of the Scribes and Pharisees,</hi> (whose lives yet (<hi>ad extra</hi>) as to all outward appearance, were as exact, as they were strict in many Religious observations <hi>we shall in no case enter into the Kingdom.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they intimate we must live, walk, and obey Gods Holy Truth and will,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95242:3"/> though by Christs assistance, yet personally &amp; more spiritually then they; Yea, they tell us what the Gospel requires from us (though it is to be done by Christ in and for us) is a more total abstinence from evil, and even lusting to it then the Law, and so the Gospel to call for more full self-denyall then the Law, if ere we live; The one saying Thou shalt not commit adultery; the other, Thou shalt not lust; the one, Thou shalt not steal; the other, Thou shalt not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet; the one, Forswear not thy self, the other, swear not all; the one, Thou shalt not kill, the other, Thou shalt not be angry without cause.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles</hi> (to <hi>go round again</hi>) They make the Law require more full and exact obedience to God, then the Gospel; <hi>The Law gives not life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perfect obedience</hi> (quoth <hi>T. D.) The Gospel gives life upon imperfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Again, They tell us <hi>one while</hi> (that is, when they preach to their people and see no <hi>Quakers</hi> among them) the same truths the Scriptures tell us concerning God, that He is of <hi>purer eyes</hi> then to behold the <hi>least iniquity,</hi> that God, John 9. 31. <hi>Accepts not, owns not, hears not</hi> sinners, says to such as work it, and <hi>depart not from iniquity; Depart from me all ye workers of iniquity, I know not whence ye are,</hi> Matt: 7. 22. Luke 13. 27. And though <hi>forgiving iniquity</hi> to the <hi>penitent,</hi> when they <hi>confesse</hi> and <hi>forsake sin,</hi> yet by no means clearing the guilty, while they lye in <hi>impaenitency</hi> under sin, Exod 34. 7. <hi>That if the heart condemn, God is greater then it,</hi> and <hi>knows all,</hi> and <hi>what the Light</hi> in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science speaks in way of that <hi>self-judgment,</hi> that's placed in us, and seconds it to <hi>justification</hi> or <hi>condemnation, accusation</hi> or <hi>excusation,</hi> there <hi>needs no witnesse to convince a man</hi> (quoth <hi>J. O.</hi> p: 43. 45. <hi>that it speaks it from God,</hi> it discovers <hi>it's Author</hi> from whom it <hi>is,</hi> &amp; in <hi>whose</hi> name it speaks; So that if that (as it does every sinner <hi>holds guilty,</hi> God, whose mind it speaks holds not <hi>guiltlesse;</hi> Yea, <hi>That he who justifies the wicked, &amp; condemns the just, even they both are abom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ination to the Lord,</hi> as Pro: 17. 15. and much more of that sort; i: e: when the <hi>Qua:</hi> tell the same truths to turn men from all sin, which is <hi>transgression</hi> or <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> [for not the least sin is <hi>equity</hi> that I know of] then, in opposition to the <hi>Qua:</hi> they wheel about, And</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles,</hi> As if God were another manner of God; Who, because its impossible by the power of his own grace to be <hi>fully freed,</hi> and <hi>perfectly purged</hi> from all sin here, will give <hi>indulgency</hi> to his <hi>sinning Saints (to go round again)</hi> They tell us other <hi>tales</hi> of him, whereby (if Pro: 17. 15. be true) they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent him as doing that, in the doing of which, he must be an <hi>abomination to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe;</hi> viz: 1. <hi>That he condemns the just,</hi> witnesse <hi>T. D.</hi> who tells us, that here the best works, and <hi>personal performances</hi> of Beleevers and Saints themselves are imperfect, sin, iniquity, dung, losse, unclean filthy rags (though done by Christ in them) And yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) That God <hi>accepts,</hi> alias, is well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased, delights, and takes pleasure in both these Beleevers and their wicked works; Witnesse the <hi>Supralapsarian, Predestination Preachers,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present God as loving of few only as <hi>Jacob,</hi> hating most men personally with <hi>Esau (qua sic</hi>) as men, <hi>the creatures of his own Creation,</hi> to shew his <hi>wrath, power, soveraignty</hi> over them, as the <hi>Potter over the Clay of the same lump</hi> (the <hi>Mistery of</hi> which matters of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Esau,</hi> their meer <hi>mans wisdom</hi> sees no more into, then a <hi>Moles</hi> eye into a <hi>Milstone</hi>) not onely before they had done either, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95242:4"/> with out reserence to either <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil foreseen</hi> to be done in time by either <hi>Adam</hi> (their supposed <hi>Representative</hi>) or <hi>themselves;</hi> and the <hi>Sublapsarians</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, who represent God as by <hi>Praeterition</hi> at least) <hi>rejecting</hi> most on the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> meerly of <hi>Adams single act,</hi> without a respect to any <hi>personall actions</hi> of their own; The least and best of which two do (doctrinally) make God a <hi>Condemner</hi> for ever of <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>just innocents;</hi> yea, very <hi>infants</hi> as they blush not to infer) for one <hi>fault</hi> of their <hi>Father Adam,</hi> for whose only <hi>eating the sowr Grapes,</hi> all the <hi>childrens teeth must be set on edge,</hi> contrary to what God sayes now, who will have that <hi>Proverb used no more,</hi> but sayes as the soul <hi>that sinneth shall dye</hi> for his own, so <hi>every man</hi> only <hi>for his own iniquity,</hi> and not <hi>the son</hi> for <hi>the fathers,</hi> any more then the <hi>father</hi> for <hi>the sons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>That he condemns</hi> not, but <hi>clears</hi> the very <hi>guilty</hi> &amp; <hi>justifies the very wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly,</hi> &amp; that not <hi>from</hi> for the <hi>Qua:</hi> know that he <hi>justifies</hi> many ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ones from</hi> their <hi>ungodlinesse,</hi> they <hi>repenting,</hi> not <hi>resisting</hi> his Spirit by which be would purg them, but giving up to become the <hi>Godly</hi> whom only <hi>he hath chosen</hi> Ps. 4.) but even <hi>in the most wicked and ungodly Actions,</hi> and even <hi>whilest under the guilt of most abominable Transgressions,</hi> so wearying the Lord, whom they <hi>speak well of sometimes</hi> as a God of <hi>True-judgment,</hi> with their <hi>evill words</hi> of him <hi>at other times, when they say,</hi> with the <hi>wicked Priests</hi> of whom God by <hi>Malachi</hi> complains ch: 2. 17. <hi>of such as do evil that they are good in the sight of the Lord, and he delighteth in them, or where is the God of judgement?</hi> as if he who <hi>changes not</hi> and said of old <hi>Shall I count them pure,</hi> &amp;c. Mic: 6. 11. did <hi>change</hi> and become another kind of God at one time, then he is at another viz: to <hi>count men righteous,</hi> even while such <hi>treasures of wickednesse are in the house of their hearts,</hi> as render them no lesse then <hi>wicked, scanty,</hi> and <hi>abominable,</hi> and <hi>to count men</hi> as I know not that ever he did <hi>pure, with their wicked ballances, &amp; with their bag of deceitful weights, while they are full of violence, and speak lyes, and their tongue is deceitful in their mouths;</hi> Witnesse not only all other his fellow <hi>Pillow-sowers under their arms,</hi> and <hi>Scothers</hi> up of <hi>sinners in their sins,</hi> and <hi>Daubers</hi> of <hi>Evill-doers</hi> with the <hi>smooth untempered Morter</hi> of their <hi>Peace, peace, when there is no peace</hi> (saith my God <hi>unto the wicked;</hi> but <hi>T. D.</hi> himself above all the rest, who p. 38. Pam: 1. not only <hi>sayes,</hi> but <hi>still stands</hi> to it, and <hi>owns</hi> it <hi>or'e</hi> and <hi>or'e</hi> again, as grosse as it is, and <hi>Justifies</hi> it for <hi>truth,</hi> in his Reply to <hi>R. H.</hi> who charges it on him [Justly] as a <hi>grosse absurdity,</hi> which I have above also more at large replyed to that <hi>David,</hi> even <hi>when he was guilty</hi> (mark that) <hi>of adultery and murder</hi> (such sins as for which the Scripture, when he lay <hi>impenitent</hi> under them, <hi>denotes</hi> and <hi>excepts</hi> him as a man <hi>not upright,</hi> a <hi>despiser of God</hi> and <hi>his Commandemenes, A doer of evil in his sight,</hi> 2 Sam: 12. whom God also had not <hi>mercy</hi> on, but did both <hi>condemn</hi> and <hi>severely judge</hi> with no lesse then <hi>Hellish horrors</hi> for <hi>his filth</hi> &amp; <hi>blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiltinesse,</hi> till he had <hi>repented for it,</hi> and was throwly <hi>purged</hi> from it, Psalm 51.) <hi>was not in a condemned, but in a just fied estate.</hi> So that the sum of <hi>T. D.</hi> and those <hi>Doctors Doctrine</hi> that side with him therein, is this; viz: (<hi>to begin the dance right) David while he commited adultery and murder,</hi> not repenting <hi>was guilty</hi> before God, and consequently not <hi>just,</hi> nor <hi>justified,</hi> but <hi>condemned,</hi> for whom God holds not <hi>guiltlesse,</hi> but <hi>guilty,</hi> they are not <hi>justified, accepted, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted, absolved, approved;</hi> but, which is all one, <hi>accused, reproved, condemned</hi> in his sight; Yet [<hi>to go round again] David while he committed adultery and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95242:4"/>
[not yet repenting] was not <hi>guilty</hi> before God, but held <hi>guiltlesse,</hi> not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,</hi> nor <hi>reprobated,</hi> or <hi>reproved,</hi> but <hi>cleared, acquitted, absolved, excused, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved;</hi> For between the two states of <hi>guilty</hi> and not <hi>guilty, non datur medium.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contradictions, Confusions, and Rounds about Liberty of Conscience.</head>
               <p n="2">II. As to the Doctrine for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> and against <hi>persecution</hi> for cause of Conscience in matters of <hi>Religion. One while</hi> they tell the world the <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrire</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of rigid imposing upon any <hi>sub penâ,</hi> or <hi>persecuting</hi> any <hi>tender Consciences</hi> for <hi>beleeving,</hi> and <hi>living</hi> according to their <hi>conviction,</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying to <hi>beleeve</hi> or <hi>live</hi> contrary thereunto, is a <hi>Bloody Tenet,</hi> a way to make more <hi>hypocrites,</hi> that for fear will <hi>conform</hi> to what they <hi>beleeve not</hi> to be truth, then true Christians, an evident note of a <hi>false Church,</hi> and <hi>Antichristian Ministry</hi> that is <hi>degenerate</hi> and <hi>apostatized</hi> from the true pure Primitive <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> which never did compel any by <hi>force</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> to be <hi>Christians,</hi> but rather suffered all sorts of sorrowes, and bare all manner of abuses from the whole world <hi>of false Worshippers,</hi> whether <hi>Heathens</hi> or <hi>Nominal Christians,</hi> barely for confessing to the truth of <hi>Christ,</hi> and testifying against the <hi>evil lives</hi> of all <hi>Christs enemies,</hi> whether such as hated the very <hi>outward name of Christ,</hi> or such <hi>as named his Name,</hi> and <hi>yet departed not from iniquity;</hi> and were every where <hi>cursed,</hi> yet <hi>blessed the cursers of them, prayed for such as persecuted them, intreated those that defamed</hi> and <hi>ill-intreated them,</hi> and were <hi>patient &amp; silent,</hi> when <hi>revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> and <hi>buffeted, beaten, banished</hi> as <hi>Vagabonds</hi> (because for truths sake they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten lest their own Homes and had no <hi>certain dwelling place</hi>) as <hi>seditious, tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, disturbers of the peace</hi> (because they <hi>peaceably</hi> went into <hi>Synagogues</hi> to reason and preach <hi>the Gospel of peace</hi>) as <hi>turners of the world upside down,</hi> because they sought to change men from their <hi>evill manners, foolish customs, vain inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>wicked wayes,</hi> that were abominable to God, and to bring them to <hi>repentance</hi> from their <hi>dead works</hi> and <hi>worships,</hi> in which their souls could never live, to <hi>worship</hi> the <hi>living God,</hi> who is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and not tyed to places, in <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in truth in the inner parts,</hi> and to turn <hi>all men</hi> from the <hi>darknesse</hi> wherein they lived in the world <hi>without,</hi> to the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Christ within</hi> themselves, and from <hi>the power of Satan unto God. Sometimes</hi> (I say) our great <hi>Gamaliels</hi> not only <hi>grant</hi> these things, but also give them out for truth to the <hi>Civill Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of the Earth, most especially then and that with no small <hi>greedinesse,</hi> when the <hi>Clergy</hi> of one kind feel themselves begin to be <hi>griped</hi> under the <hi>greedy clut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of another <hi>colour,</hi> when they are likely to be <hi>imposed upon</hi> by others, and to be clapped down under hatches by the <hi>Clerical cruelties</hi> of each other <hi>respectively;</hi> As for example, where ever the <hi>Papal,</hi> or <hi>Roman,</hi> or else the <hi>Presbiterian Primacy</hi> keeps the Keys, &amp; spreads their <hi>Black Eagles claws</hi> over all others, &amp; hath the power of <hi>permitting</hi> or <hi>poenal imposing,</hi> there the <hi>Prelatick Pastoralty</hi> pleads his <hi>priviledge</hi> to have the <hi>liberty</hi> of his <hi>Liturgy</hi> (he behaving himselfe no otherwise then <hi>peaceably</hi>) among them. Where the <hi>Episcopal Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> holds his <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> and is Supream there, as the <hi>Papal</hi> would willingly have his liberty (and I blame none, neither <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> nor <hi>Heathens</hi> for desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the like, to walk every one in the <hi>Name of his God,</hi> Mich; 4.) So both that <hi>Right-rigid Scottish Presbiterian Race,</hi> and that <hi>Mongrill seed</hi> of loose <hi>Independent-Presbiters,</hi> are more <hi>loud</hi> for <hi>liberty</hi> then any other sort of <hi>Sectaries</hi> (so called) whatsoever, who do all <hi>no lesse rationally</hi> then they [they demeaning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95242:5"/>
                  <hi>peaceably</hi> (as the very Principle of the Quakers binds them to do to all men) require each the <hi>peaceable enjoyment</hi> of his <hi>Religion, Church-Ministry, fellowship, faith</hi> and <hi>way of Worship</hi> under them; When the <hi>Rabbies</hi> are ready to be <hi>Ridden</hi> one by another (witnesse the <hi>Outcries</hi> once of <hi>New-England</hi> against <hi>Old,</hi> when under the <hi>heat</hi> of far lesse <hi>Persecution</hi> from the <hi>Bishops,</hi> then they have acted since themselves. <hi>Old England</hi> it self was too hot to hold them, also the present pleadings, not only for their <hi>Directorian Liberties,</hi> but (<hi>Turpe et miserabile</hi>) their very <hi>Livings, Tythes Preferments,</hi> and their <hi>Places,</hi> now the <hi>Common Prayer Book Priesthood,</hi> whom they unhorsed, hath his <hi>foot</hi> in the <hi>Stirrup</hi> again, and may not unlikely <hi>push the Presbiter</hi> besides the <hi>Saddle</hi>) then, Oh then, what <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Cry</hi> against the <hi>bloody Tenet</hi> of <hi>Persecution,</hi> and <hi>grievous groans</hi> for this <hi>desire of all Nations</hi> and <hi>People, Liberty of Conscience, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conscience,</hi> do we dayly hear from <hi>Smectimnuus</hi> his <hi>own,</hi> as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>mouthes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhyles</hi> again, yea ever when the <hi>Clergy</hi> of any one <hi>colour,</hi> hath by either <hi>craft</hi> or <hi>conquest</hi> catcht the Keyes of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and <hi>archi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ved the Holy chaire,</hi> they straightway <hi>clap</hi> their <hi>cruell clawes</hi> upon them, to the keeping down by force of <hi>Armes</hi> more then <hi>Arguments</hi> all <hi>Liberty</hi> for any <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences but their own.</hi> Then (to <hi>go round again) come let us sing a new Song,</hi> Behold cry the <hi>Counsellers</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the <hi>People of the children of Israell are more &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 1. 9, 10, 11. <hi>As Pharoah said unto his people, Behold, the people of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Israel are more and mightier then we. Come on, let us deal wisely with them, lest they multiply, and it come to passe, that when there falls out any war, they joyn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so unto our enemies, and fight against us, and so get them up out of the Land. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they did set over them Taskmasters to afflict them with their burdens, and they built for Pharoah Treasure cities, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thom and Raamses.</hi> Then they set <hi>Taskmasters.</hi> Then say the <hi>Sanballats</hi> and <hi>Tobiasses,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Ashdodite,</hi> as they Neh. 4. 1, 2, 7, 8, 11. <hi>But it came to passe that when Sanballat heard that we builded the wall, he was wroth and took great indignation, and mocked the Jews. And he spake before his brethren, and the army of Samaria, and said, What do these feeble Jews? will they fortifie themselves? will they sacrifice? will they make an end in a day? will they revive the stones out of the heaps of rubbish which are burnt? But it came to passe that when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites heard that the walls of Jerusalem were made up, and that the breaches began to be stopped, then they were very wroth, And conspired all of them together, to come, and to fight against Jerusalem, and to hinder it. And our adversaries said, they shall not know, neither see, till we come in the midst among them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease.</hi> Then call they out for the help of <hi>Prisons,</hi> and <hi>punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, cruel mockings</hi> and <hi>scourgings, Pillorings gaggings, draggings before Rulers, accusations</hi> to <hi>Magistrates, condemnings</hi> at <hi>Judgement-seats, cutting off ears slitting noses▪ fines, confis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ations, stockings, &amp; sloanings, beatings, buffetings, brandings. Borings, Banishings, Hangings, Burnings,</hi> as men no more fit to live among men nor on the earth, of such as <hi>conforme</hi> not to their <hi>conceits,</hi> as <hi>fall not down</hi> before what ever <hi>Golden Image</hi> they set up; then the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> like those Mic. 3. that cryed <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> begin to <hi>bite with their Teeth,</hi> and to <hi>prepare War</hi> against all whose <hi>consciences</hi> cannot own them as their <hi>own</hi> and <hi>Christs Ministers,</hi> so as to put <hi>into their Mouths,</hi> then away with all such fellowes from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95242:5"/> their <hi>Families</hi> to <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Consistoryes, holes</hi> and <hi>dungeons, haile</hi> them from their <hi>houses,</hi> tear them and theirs to pieces for our <hi>Tithes, spoile</hi> and make <hi>havock</hi> of their <hi>Goods,</hi> let their <hi>Relations</hi> perish and beg <hi>their bread,</hi> let their <hi>children be fatherlesse</hi> and their <hi>wives widows;</hi> This and the like <hi>Divinity</hi> is <hi>divined</hi> out from among the <hi>Divines,</hi> to the <hi>contradicting</hi> of themselves as to that <hi>doctrine of liberty of conscience,</hi> they were most devoted to, while they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>sufferers</hi> under one another; Witnesse (as I faid) the <hi>sad sufferings</hi> of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of <hi>Truths truest friends,</hi> not only to <hi>bloody whippings, beatings, banishments,</hi> and <hi>bonds,</hi> but also to the <hi>Death</hi> of their bodyes by <hi>hanging</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi> of late, who had, not long since, fled out of <hi>Old-Englvud</hi> for their <hi>conscience sake,</hi> and for fear (comparatively to their own <hi>fearful fleaings of Christs flock</hi>) of but a few <hi>Flea-bitings</hi> by the <hi>Bishops,</hi> witnesse also what <hi>I. O.</hi> himself, an <hi>High-Priest</hi> who soon forgot that ere he was <hi>Clark,</hi> not only did in his <hi>Vicechancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorship,</hi> but also would have had done, had he had his own will, who when by his <hi>loudnesse</hi> for it, he had got not only a <hi>liberty</hi> for his conscience, to very <hi>loosenesse</hi> and <hi>licentiousresse,</hi> but also a <hi>large livelihood</hi> for his own carkasse, not only many other wayes abused the <hi>Qua:</hi> who <hi>disturbed</hi> nothing but that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that will be destroyed; but also in the place aforesaid, Exer: 3. S. 39. be speaks the whole world on behalfe of that <hi>innocent people,</hi> for nothing but teaching that <hi>innocent doctrine</hi> of <hi>freedom from all sin, &amp; perfecting holinesse</hi> in this life (which <hi>T. D.</hi> and <hi>T. Rumsy</hi> also wish as well to, as to any <hi>doctrine of devils,</hi> by which name they also call it) to this tune, <hi>Fanaticos non esse perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos testimonio sunt illorum mendu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia, fraudes, scelera, hypocrisis; iis vero qui immunes se esse ab his omnibus aliis{que} peccatis vel levissimis impudenter gloriantur, punitiones et incarcerationes, quas Akatastasia sua sibi ultro accersunt, esse debeant; That the Qua: are not perfect their lyes, frauds, hainous crimes and hypocrisies do testifie to us, but to them who impudently glory</hi> (so indeed the <hi>Qua:</hi> do not but assert that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom attainable) <hi>that they are free from all these and other sins, even the least</hi> the more purity it seemsmen come to the more to be punisht <hi>with</hi> him) <hi>punishments and Prisons, which by their tumultuousnesse</hi> (such as that of <hi>Paul</hi> and other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, 2 Cor. 7. were proved to be Christs Ministers by) <hi>they voluntarily pull on themselves</hi> (as the Saints and Christ ever did by exposing themselves to their malice for mens souls sakes ought to be; for which wickednesse of <hi>working</hi> &amp; <hi>wishing</hi> that <hi>evil</hi> to others, which they would not, when they were under others willingly have done to thēselves, hath the Lord who avengeth the cause of his poor people, who had rather <hi>suffer persecution</hi> ever, then either <hi>act it</hi> themselves, or wish that any for meer conscience (<hi>though blinded</hi>) should suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by it; yea God, who <hi>judgeth</hi> all truly according to their own <hi>false judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of others, <hi>justly meteth</hi> out to that <hi>hypocriticall generation,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that with <hi>Capernaum</hi> clim'b <hi>up to Heaven</hi> in Forms and sair words, and fine shews, but are now brought <hi>down to Hell,</hi> the same <hi>measure they meted</hi> to his people, and will I doubt not in due time (except they yet repent) do the like to those <hi>holy hypocrites</hi> of <hi>New-England:</hi> And let those <hi>Priests,</hi> who have now the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, take heed</hi> of <hi>pushing</hi> too hard against the <hi>pricks,</hi> is my desire to them for their <hi>own souls,</hi> who are every way concerned to be wary of that <hi>wonted way</hi> of <hi>wearing out, wearying</hi> and <hi>worrying</hi> of <hi>Christs little flock</hi> for not <hi>feeding</hi> and <hi>cloathing,</hi> with their <hi>Fleeces,</hi> such <hi>Shepheards,</hi> as do not <hi>feed them:</hi> And that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95242:6"/> the <hi>King</hi> and all the <hi>Powers</hi> that <hi>subordinately act</hi> under Him, may so far <hi>know in this their day what makes for their externall, internall, and eternal peace,</hi> as not to be found fighters against God, nor to <hi>touch those anointed ones, for whose sakes God hath of old,</hi> and will again rebuke great Kings and Nations, whose true intent is not to use any <hi>carnal weapons</hi> against any, but to let his <hi>Prophets, Lambs,</hi> and <hi>Little ones</hi> alone to <hi>live a peaceable and quiet life under them in all godlinesse and honesly,</hi> As 'tis the <hi>best good</hi> I can, so 'tis the <hi>worst hurt</hi> I do wish to him and them: For of a truth the <hi>Lord</hi> himself is risen up for the help of his <hi>own seed,</hi> against all that slayes it, and if they hearken to the hasty <hi>hue</hi> and <hi>cry</hi> of such <hi>Priests,</hi> as cry out to them for help against his Saints, when the Lord ariseth once more <hi>against the house of the evil-doers, and against the help of them that work iniquity,</hi> and stretcheth out his hand again (as undoubtedly he will do to deliver his <hi>ransomed ones</hi> that are found in <hi>innocency</hi> toward the King and all men, <hi>both he that helpeth shall fall, and he that is holpen shall fall, and they shall all fail together</hi> of their expected ends, and aim to root <hi>out the seed of Israel,</hi> for the mouth of the Lord of Hosts hath spoken it, Isa. 31. 2, 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be wise now therefore O King, be instructed O ye Judges of</hi> this English Nation, <hi>serve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce before him</hi> (in this day wherein he hath lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up your heads) <hi>with trembling;</hi> Oppose him not by your <hi>interpositions</hi> and <hi>impositions</hi> in his own <hi>Court,</hi> which is the <hi>Conscience,</hi> for <hi>let Heathenish people rage and imagine what they will, let earthly Kings set themselves, &amp; Rulers take counsel together</hi> as they will, its in vain if against <hi>the Lord, and his anointed Christ Jesus his Son in his Saints, whom he will set as his King</hi> in the Conscience, <hi>and in his holy hill of Sion:</hi> But rather <hi>kisse the Son lest he be angry, and ye perish for</hi> ever <hi>from the way of your</hi> own peace, <hi>for if his wrath be kindled, yea but a little, blessed are all they only that trust</hi> and hope <hi>in him,</hi> Psal. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contradictions and Rounds about the modern infallible teachings of Gods infallible Spirit.</head>
               <p n="3">III. As to our doctrine of the present <hi>guidance</hi> of <hi>Christs Church</hi> and <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry</hi> by his own <hi>infallible spirit;</hi> They tell us sometimes, or at least yeeld to us when we tell them, <hi>that at this day</hi> they only, that are led by <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> are the <hi>Sons of God,</hi> that if any have not <hi>Christs Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>guidance</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which is an <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> and <hi>guidance</hi> (for we know no <hi>fallible Spirit</hi> that he hath, nor <hi>fallible guidance</hi> that that Spirit hath) which leads <hi>undoubtedly</hi> all men and Ministers that follow it, and not the lustings of the flesh against it, into <hi>no sin,</hi> out of <hi>all errour,</hi> into <hi>all truth,</hi> being <hi>truth it</hi> selfe and <hi>no lye,</hi> and that some there are now, that are <hi>led</hi> of that <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>walk after it,</hi> and not <hi>after the flesh,</hi> as then there were, Rom: 8. Gal: 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By and by</hi> (they finding themselves <hi>erring and contradicting</hi> one another, and no <hi>betier guided</hi> in things of God then by their <hi>own thoughts, uncertain conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, crooked conceits,</hi> whereby they crosse one another in their <hi>several senses &amp; meanings,</hi> about the <hi>one mind of Christ,</hi> in that <hi>one writing,</hi> which they call their <hi>Rule</hi>) because they follow their own <hi>flashy fancies,</hi> and not the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and measuring all others by themselves (<hi>To go round again</hi>) they tell us another thing, and make it no lesse then a matter of <hi>meer pretence</hi> and <hi>high presumption,</hi> not so much as safely to be <hi>supposed</hi> that a man should be now <hi>Theopnuestos, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely inspired,</hi> or <hi>infallibly guided</hi> by <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> in these dayes, as if that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95242:6"/> did not continue his <hi>infallible,</hi> but afforded only some kind of <hi>fallible gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> to his <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>Ministry</hi> now, and led them, as <hi>R. B. J. T.</hi> also say the Light within did the Heathen p. 68. <hi>in somethings well, in most into crooked and dangerous wayes,</hi> and that makes these men sometimes bid men <hi>Attend and take heed to it, sometimes</hi> again (<hi>cane pejus et angue) reject, detest,</hi> and <hi>take heed of it,</hi> as I shall shew more by and by; Witnesse <hi>J. O.</hi> in the places above talkt with, where he talks down all <hi>Divine inspiration</hi> and <hi>guidance</hi> now a dayes by the <hi>infallible spirit,</hi> as matters but <hi>falsely pretended</hi> to, p. 5, 6. 63. 167. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>T. D.</hi> who denys his <hi>own Ministry</hi> to be <hi>infallible</hi> and thereby proclaming those to be but fools who follow it, accuses the <hi>Qua:</hi> of <hi>false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> with a <hi>witnesse,</hi> for once offering to affirm this truth that theirs (which yet <hi>is truly Christs Ministry</hi>) is <hi>infallible:</hi> As (quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h he) <hi>to the infallibillity of their Ministry,</hi> 3 Jurates of <hi>Sandwich will testifie that they did affirm their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry to be infallible:</hi> Which if it were not (say I) I would yeeld our selves to be as <hi>very fools</hi> who suffer for it, as those would be who also <hi>suffer</hi> for attending to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contradictions, Confusions &amp; Rounds concerning the large love and rich mercy of God to all mankind.</head>
               <p n="4">IV. As to the doctrine of Gods <hi>great grace, universal love,</hi> and rich mercy to all men, they extoll it in their <hi>Proclamations</hi> of it <hi>one while</hi> as an <hi>infinite, boundlesse, bottomlesse Bounty, matchlesse Mercy, endlesse Large love, exceeding rich grace,</hi> listing up their voyces among all people to this, or the like tune; <hi>O the rich, infinite, unexpressible, unconceiveable, incomprehensible love of God</hi> in Christ Iesus <hi>to all mankind,</hi> to the <hi>whole world, so hath he loved the world</hi> (a <hi>sic</hi> without a <hi>sicut) that he gave his only begotten son that whosoever beleeves in him might not perish, but have everlasting life: God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world, but that the world through him might be saved, he is not willing any one of you should perish, but that all should come to repentance, and be saved in the acknowledgement of his truth.</hi> Therefore <hi>Ho every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters, come and buy Wine &amp; Milke, but without mony, without price;</hi> God is free of what he hath (onely the <hi>Priests</hi> (that have freely received, and should as freely give) give them their Fees, let them have <hi>Money,</hi> and <hi>Price,</hi> and <hi>Pay,</hi> and <hi>Augmentations,</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> enough) God looks for nothing. <hi>Come unto Christ all ye that labour and are heavy laden, here's rest for all, your souls: The Spirit and the Bride say come, and who ever will, let him come and take of the water of life freely:</hi> Obje: Oh but we are <hi>sinners,</hi> will God own us? <hi>Answ:</hi> Art thou a <hi>sinner?</hi> then who ere thou art, thou art one of those <hi>Christ</hi> came to save, <hi>he came to save that which was lost, to take away the sins of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj: Oh but we are <hi>great sinners, wicked wretches,</hi> such as never were the like, multiplying sins, transgressions, is there any hope for us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ: If we confesse our sins he is faithful and just to forgive them, pardoning ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, transgression and sin, Christ hath received gifts for the rebellious, he tasted death for every man, he is a propitiation</hi> not for some only, but also for <hi>the sins of the whole world;</hi> He opens the door of salvation to all, <hi>His tender mercies are over all his works,</hi> he delights to magnifie his mercy <hi>above all; it rejoyceth against judgement;</hi> Come all and welcome, none shall be cast off in any wise that come to him, he would have all to come, he is not willing that any should
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95242:7"/> perish: <hi>Behold I bring you glad tydings of great joy</hi> to all people, a Saviour is borne unto them, from God, theres <hi>peace proclaimed, good wi towards men;</hi> Though they are enemies to him by wicked works, yet <hi>God is in Christ reconciling the world to himselfe, not imputing trespasses</hi> to any that will <hi>be reconciled unto him;</hi> He swears <hi>that he hath no pleasure in the death of him that dyeth, but had much rather that the wicked should turn from his wickednesse and live,</hi> and therefore he hath sent his Son <hi>a Light to the Nations, and so to be his Salvation, even to the ends of the earth,</hi> and this he also <hi>declares</hi> to men as <hi>his good will</hi> to them <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>calling to all</hi> to <hi>look</hi> to him and <hi>be saved, universally, freely, truly</hi> (without mockage) <hi>tendering peace to all, offering salvation to all men, intending</hi> no otherwayes then he sayes, that every individual that turns to him shall have it, and hath wrought in them <hi>to will and to do,</hi> and now would have them <hi>will &amp; do,</hi> hath given every one a <hi>Talent,</hi> in which <hi>Trading</hi> he shall enter into the joy, but being <hi>unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> with, and not <hi>improving,</hi> thereupon only they are <hi>shut out;</hi> and abundance more of the like, which is all precious, and the plain truth of the Scripture, which they call the revealed will of God, according to which only we must judge of Gods mind to man-ward.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles</hi> again, that is, when the <hi>Qua:</hi> come to question them before their people whether it be so in very deed or no, as they say, that God is so much more prone to <hi>mercy</hi> then <hi>severity,</hi> and is so <hi>truly loving</hi> to all <hi>mankind, to all sinner</hi> (and so consequently to <hi>all men,</hi> for all are but <hi>sinners</hi>) provided they accept his grace given, and improve it, &amp; be not wanting to themselves, and come to him, &amp; whether he would <hi>honestly</hi> &amp; <hi>heartily</hi> (as he says) that all should come and would come, and would not have them, <hi>ponere obicem,</hi> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their <hi>Salvation,</hi> and put <hi>it away from them,</hi> and that God as truly <hi>intends</hi> their good, as they <hi>extend</hi> the newes of it, if men refuse not the offer and would indeed have them accept of the offer and not slight it?</p>
               <p>Then O come let us sing a new song (<hi>To go round again) The divine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of Gods <hi>universal love</hi> is drawn in again, as <hi>damnable heresie,</hi> and his <hi>grace niggarded</hi> up into a <hi>Corner,</hi> and his <hi>mighty mercy</hi> diminisht into a mite, and a Tale told us that this is but a <hi>generall outside profer,</hi> he <hi>intends not truly that all shall come</hi> to him by repentance, and have benefit by the death of his Son, <hi>he dyed not for all,</hi> but though its said <hi>All, every man,</hi> by <hi>all</hi> he means but a <hi>few,</hi> and he hath not put <hi>all</hi> so much as into <hi>a capacity,</hi> or <hi>common possibility</hi> of life by his Son, nor into so much as an <hi>ability</hi> to come to him, the most <hi>can't chuse life</hi> that they may live, they may <hi>chuse death</hi> that they may dye, and <hi>must chuse that,</hi> being afore of old <hi>ordained to condemnation,</hi> and so though <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>misery, blessing</hi> and <hi>cursing</hi> be set before them, and they bid to <hi>chuse,</hi> yet their <hi>wills</hi> must of necessity <hi>chuse</hi> the <hi>curse,</hi> having it not wrought in them (as a few have) so much as to <hi>will</hi> and to <hi>do</hi> any good, and so though they have <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evill</hi> to chuse, which they will of the two, yet when all's done, as the case is, they must (<hi>Hobsons</hi> choice) cleave to the evil, and chuse whether they will have that or none, having not only no <hi>arbitrium liberum,</hi> but not so much as <hi>liberatum,</hi> they are yet <hi>lockt</hi> up to a Post by <hi>Adams fall</hi> 6000 years before they were born, and were never <hi>unloosed</hi> to this day, nor ever must be, so as to be at <hi>liberty</hi> to come when they are call'd, and yet must be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned too for not coming. they have <hi>enough</hi> given them to <hi>leave them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95242:7"/> without excuse &amp; damn them,</hi> but <hi>Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n sub nulla considerationem,</hi> quoth <hi>J. O.</hi> Exer: 4. Christ in no case hath given a <hi>saving light</hi> to all, nor God <hi>grace suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to save them,</hi> unto them all: <hi>Christ, Comfort,</hi> thats the <hi>childrens bread,</hi> it belongs not to the <hi>dogs, Christ dyed</hi> and is given only for the <hi>world of the elect</hi> that beleeve, but the most not only do not, but cannot beleeve; And besides there's no <hi>Saviour</hi> for the most to <hi>beleeve in</hi> (as theirs being sent in <hi>Gods love</hi> but to a <hi>few,</hi> so that if the most, if all should beleeve him to <hi>be theirs,</hi> the most must <hi>beleeve a lye,</hi> for 'tis not so, yet (<hi>To go round again</hi>) this withall they must know that they must be <hi>condemned</hi> for not <hi>beleeving a lye▪</hi> for not <hi>beleeving</hi> that, <hi>which if they should all beleeve, the most must</hi> beleeve a lye; <hi>For he that beleeves not is condemned, because he beleeves not in the only begotten Son of God,</hi> and this and no other thing is their <hi>condemnation,</hi> but <hi>because Christ</hi> is come a <hi>light into the world,</hi> and they come not to it, beleeve not in it, <hi>but love the darknesse more then it</hi> otherwise Christ came not <hi>into the world to condemn the very world</hi> (which is condemned) <hi>but</hi> to this intent <hi>that the world throw him might be saved.</hi> And (<hi>to go round again</hi>) though they are sent to make such fair <hi>proffers, promises, and large Proclamations of Gods love,</hi> yet this is but <hi>his revealed will,</hi> he does but do this to make men beleeve he is <hi>so loving to them,</hi> as to give his own Son for them, that if they beleeve i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not as he knows they cannot, faith being his gift, and that which he will give but to sew, and leave the most unable to beleeve) he may come the more in wrath against a hundred <hi>to one of mankind,</hi> and take <hi>vengeance</hi> on them for their not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that <hi>false Testimony,</hi> which in his <hi>revealed will</hi> he gives by us of his Son, but he hath a <hi>secret will,</hi> hidden from us, wherein he <hi>far otherwise peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> decrees, that but a <hi>few only shall be saved,</hi> and this (though <hi>hidden</hi> from us) we declare to be of the twain the very truth indeed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cum multis aliis ejusdem fursuris, quae nunc praescribere longum est.</head>
               <p>Just as if, a thousand men fast settered up in Prison, standing <hi>all</hi> condemned to be hanged, a <hi>messenger</hi> should be sent from a <hi>King,</hi> in whose power it is to <hi>save</hi> or <hi>slay</hi> them <hi>All</hi> on what Terms he pleases, to proclaim the <hi>good-Newes,</hi> and the <hi>Glad-Tidings</hi> of pardon and life to them <hi>All,</hi> and <hi>the wonderfull mercy</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> to them <hi>All,</hi> as one <hi>more prone</hi> by far <hi>to mercy then wrath,</hi> in such wise and to such a purpose as followes:</p>
               <p>O ye <hi>poor undon lost men,</hi> ye lye now at the <hi>mercy of the King, dead men All,</hi> but <hi>behold</hi> I am come from him to bring <hi>glad tidings of great joy</hi> to you <hi>All, lift up your heads, chear up your hearts,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> that he may shew he delights more in <hi>saving</hi> then <hi>destroying,</hi> in <hi>mercy</hi> then <hi>wrath,</hi> though for displeasing him, not personally, but paternally, in your <hi>fathers</hi> loins, he has <hi>advantage</hi> to cut you <hi>All</hi> off, yet he is resolved to save <hi>one of you</hi> and hang but 999, and he would every man of, you beleeve it for himself that its he in <hi>particular</hi> he comes to, and not to the rest; And yet <hi>to go round again</hi>) Conditionally that <hi>every man</hi> of you beleeve it for himself, it is to <hi>every such individual</hi> indeed, &amp; <hi>consequently</hi> both to one and all the rest, and if ye all unloose your selves out of the Chains and come away (but that ye can't do, and 'tis not his will ye should, and none must give you the keyes) ye shall all be spared, and I know not which that <hi>elect one is</hi> for my part, nor which of you <hi>All</hi> it is he in tends <hi>absolutely</hi> to spare, that lyes in his <hi>secret will,</hi> but I am sent with his <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95242:8"/> will</hi> to tell you that he that can beleeve it, its he that is to be favoured, he is the <hi>man</hi> who ere it is, and though (I am sure his love) is to but <hi>one,</hi> and 999 are peremptorily, personally, possitively <hi>ordained</hi> to <hi>dye;</hi> Yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) If ye all beleeve his love to you, ye shall <hi>All live,</hi> if any dye 'tis <hi>his own fault,</hi> because he <hi>beleeves not the Kings love to him,</hi> and comes not away out of his Fetters, and <hi>nothing else,</hi> and though he can't come out of his Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet let him know its but just that I should leave him there▪ because his father offended the King before he was born, its enough for them that he is so <hi>rich in mercy</hi> to the whole thousand, as to save one, and proclaim <hi>salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to <hi>All,</hi> with no intent of <hi>pardon,</hi> that he may take the more advantage on the rest by their <hi>refusal to come,</hi> when <hi>they cannot,</hi> to do <hi>execution</hi> on them with ten fold more <hi>wrath, rigour</hi> and <hi>severity,</hi> then if the pardon never had been <hi>proclaimed</hi> to them at all.</p>
               <p>In much what such a <hi>rambling, confused, self contradictory</hi> manner do our <hi>Nationall-Messengers</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Gods grace (Consideratis considerandis</hi>) hold out their <hi>Gospell</hi> to <hi>All men</hi> as <hi>Embassadours</hi> from God to them <hi>All. One while extolling,</hi> &amp; <hi>extending</hi> it over all Gods works to <hi>All men,</hi> and <hi>otherwhiles,</hi> when they have carryed it about long in a vast <hi>circuit</hi> and <hi>circumference</hi> of <hi>Commendatory conference (To go round again</hi>) in their <hi>niggardly News-books</hi> they wind it about, and wrap it all up within the narrow corner of their conceited <hi>wheel,</hi> within a <hi>wheel,</hi> or <hi>little world</hi> of a few Elect ones only, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating it till they all most quite extinguish it in their talk, &amp; preach it wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh into nothing: Witnesse <hi>J. O.</hi> (as is shewed more at large in the book aforesaid) and <hi>T. D.</hi> also telling us indeed that <hi>God offers Salvation to All men,</hi> but intends it only <hi>to a few.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contradictions, Confusions, and Rounds about the doctrine of perfect freedom from sin attainable in this life.</head>
               <p n="5">V. As to Salvation from sin in this life, which Christ gives to all that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in his light. <hi>One while</hi> they teach it to us themselves as attainable here by the grace of God, as the <hi>Qua:</hi> do, in these or the like deliveryes of themselves in their preachings and writings according to the <hi>Scriptures; People ye must deny all ungodlinesse and worldly lusts, and live Godly, righteously, and soberly</hi> (mark) <hi>in this present world;</hi> The <hi>grace of God</hi> that bringeth salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to such as take heed to it, and receive <hi>it not in vain, appears to All men,</hi> and <hi>teaches</hi> them so to live, but that they turn <hi>from it and turn it into wantonnesse, and if we walk in the Light as God is in the Light, we then have fellowship with him</hi> (who hath none with <hi>sin and sinners</hi>) and not only so, but also <hi>the blood of Jesus Christ his son cleanseth us from All sin,</hi> and though we cannot <hi>say we have no sin,</hi> since we and all men have sinned, yet <hi>if we confess our sins God is faithful</hi> not only to <hi>forgive us our sins</hi> past, but (which is a further matter) <hi>to cleanse us from All unrighleousnesle: Having therefore such promises let us cleanse our selves from</hi> (mark) <hi>All filthiness of flesh and spirit</hi> (who knows any more then all) <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting holiness in Gods fear;</hi> The <hi>blessed men,</hi> Psal. 119. 3. are the Saints or Holy Ones <hi>that do no iniquity but walk in Gods way</hi> and though ye think well of your selves because your sins are little, yet no sin is so little, but if liv'd &amp; died in, its damning, therefore take heed of the <hi>least iniquityes,</hi> &amp; while ye have time and space given you to repent from them in, leave, forsake, foregoe them, <hi>live</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95242:8"/> according to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which allows of no sin, which is <hi>written that men might not sin,</hi> which is <hi>able through faith to make a man of God perfect and wise to salvation from</hi> sin, which is <hi>perfect</hi> to its own end, which is Salvation, <hi>which end</hi> it <hi>attains not hereafter,</hi> for its of no use then, and therefore must do it here, or no where, so that if you dye in the least of your sins (unrepented from) <hi>better ye had never been born,</hi> for there's no <hi>Purgatory</hi> in the world to come as the <hi>Pope</hi> fains, but as the <hi>Tree falls it lyes, as death leaves you, judgement finds you,</hi> if ye lye down in your Graves in your <hi>sins,</hi> you will rise out of them full of <hi>sorrowes:</hi> Listen unto Christs Ministers, who are given <hi>for the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, for the perfecting of the Saints, the edifying of the body, till we all come to a Perfect man, to the measure of the stature of the fullnesle of Christ</hi> himselfe, so as <hi>to be as he is in this world, and whoever saith he abides in him ought so to walk as himselfe walked in whom was no sin: and who hath true hope in him purifieth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe as he also is pure;</hi> and a multitude more sayings of like sort we may hear them utter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles</hi> (that is when the Qua: call men to the same living without sin, telling them these things are <hi>possible</hi> to be done by <hi>Gods grace,</hi> who of his <hi>good pleasure hath wrought in men to will and to do,</hi> so that by the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency</hi> of that they may now work out their <hi>own salvation,</hi> if they neglect not this day of Gods <hi>long suffering</hi> and <hi>salvation,</hi> wherein God would succour them if they will, and that God requires not by either his <hi>Ministets</hi> or their <hi>Scriptures, Impossibilities</hi> from his creatures under such <hi>poenalty</hi> as <hi>eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> if not performed) then (<hi>to go round again</hi>) they tell us other matters, which (as <hi>contradictory</hi> as they are to those above-said) we must notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing (or else be held for <hi>Hereticks</hi>) believe from them to be the <hi>truth, viz.</hi> That <hi>tis most false to affirm that the Scripture</hi> (the <hi>perfection</hi> whereof they plead to lye, <hi>in nullâ aliâ re,</hi> in no other thing then its <hi>sufficiency to its</hi> end, which it can't attain hereafter (if not here) sith there it ceases as to all its uses) <hi>either doth or can obtain its end</hi> (which end they say also is <hi>salvation</hi> from the sin that destroyes the soul) <hi>dum in hoc mundo haeremus</hi> (so sayes I. O. Ex. 3.) <hi>while we have a being in this World.</hi> Then they make as if the <hi>Ministry</hi> of them who wrote the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> were such as their <hi>own</hi> is, viz. a meer <hi>Antick mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age</hi> of men, a <hi>conclave of contradictions, confusions, absurdities and Rounds,</hi> a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry of flat falsities</hi> (not to say <hi>fooleries</hi>) a <hi>mad-message</hi> of <hi>impossibilities,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they stand all their dayes calling upon all men for money (as <hi>Homines Domini</hi>) in <hi>Nomine Domini</hi> in the name of God on <hi>pain of</hi> his <hi>eternall displeasure</hi> and their <hi>damnation,</hi> to do what they are to believe to as an <hi>Article of their Faith</hi> on pain of the <hi>Hereticks condemnation, All men</hi> can never <hi>possibly</hi> do, God <hi>empowering</hi> but very <hi>few</hi> by <hi>true grace</hi> to do ought <hi>at all</hi> of what he requires; nay not <hi>empowering any one</hi> at all to do all that, viz. to <hi>cease from all sinning</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him in the time of this life, wherein he requires it to be done by them; as being <hi>never possible</hi> to be done in that to come if neglected here: Yea then the <hi>Doctrine of full freedome from sin here is contrary to the Tenour of the Scripture,</hi> (quoth T. D.) yea in short no better nor worse then a very <hi>doctrine of Devils</hi> (quoth T. D. and T. <hi>Rumsey</hi> both in their Book, which is so largely answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red already in mine above said.)</p>
               <p>So then we have the Ministers mind in this poynt <hi>tripliciter</hi> or rather <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drupliciter</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95242:9"/> at least about the time of the Saints perfect purgation from all sin. First, It is <hi>somewhere</hi> that they all confesse at first. Secondly, 'Tis <hi>not here</hi> in this World, (cry they) that comes too near the <hi>Copyhold</hi> of the Qua: and we would not be <hi>ensnared</hi> with their beguiling Doctrine. Thirdly, 'Tis <hi>not in that to come</hi> (cry they) this puts us <hi>poynt blank</hi> into the <hi>Purgatory of the Pope:</hi> We must <hi>beware</hi> of that, lest <hi>fleeing</hi> too farre from the <hi>Qua:</hi> snare we fall into the <hi>Papists pit.</hi> Fourthly, 'tis not in any World between this and that to come, for there's no such <hi>middle World</hi> that we know of; therefore Fifthly, (to <hi>goe quite round</hi> to where we were before we began, for <hi>Incidit in Scyllam qui vult vit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re Charybdim</hi>) It's <hi>somewhere</hi> (as we said at first) but we <hi>know not where;</hi> which (<hi>to go round again</hi>) is as much as to say (for ought we know) just <hi>no-where</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>Howbeit some are not so well aware yet of the Traps they talk themselves into thereby, but that they will be taking on them precisely to determine where it is when we closely urge them; but their Testimony hangs as hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somely, and is as well tangled together as the links of a pair of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thangers,</hi> whereof every one draws a different way from another, for some if askt when the full purging is; <hi>it is</hi> (say they) <hi>while the soul is passing between here and heaven after its departed from the body; This as</hi> A. P. <hi>informes me was</hi> T. Ds. <hi>answer to</hi> L. H. <hi>when askt at</hi> Sandwich <hi>in an assambly of many the precise time and period of the perfect purging;</hi> so making a <hi>purgatory after death</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, which it seems is in the <hi>aire,</hi> and therein only different from the <hi>Popes,</hi> which is feigned to be <hi>under the earth:</hi> Others that I have put the <hi>Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to, say tis a <hi>little before the soul departs out of the body,</hi> to whom when I have redoubled my <hi>Query</hi> thus; <hi>if a little</hi> before the soul depart why not a <hi>little sooner,</hi> sith <hi>before</hi> is but <hi>before</hi> let it be a <hi>longer</hi> or a <hi>lesser</hi> while? and if a <hi>minute,</hi> why not an <hi>hour?</hi> if an <hi>hour,</hi> why not a <hi>day?</hi> and so (<hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> the same means attended to) why not a <hi>month,</hi> a <hi>year,</hi> and <hi>years,</hi> many as well as few? I have received no answer and good reason why, because there's none to give; and so we take it for granted from them that it's <hi>before death,</hi> however as we say (if at all) though these contradict T. D. who sayes, with the Pope, it's after death: Others not knowing which to say, seeing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Argument, which is thus, viz. <hi>perfect purging,</hi> if at all, must be <hi>in this World</hi> as the <hi>Qua;</hi> say, or in that <hi>to come</hi> as the <hi>Pope</hi> says, who feigns a <hi>Purgatory</hi> there for the remnant of sins that remain unpurged away here, or else in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, <hi>betwixt</hi> this and that to come, which <hi>Chimaera</hi> who ere heard of? being now somewhat wary lest if they say <hi>before</hi> the soul go out, which is in <hi>this World,</hi> they yield to the Qua: and if <hi>after</hi> it's gone out which is the <hi>World to come,</hi> they appeare too near <hi>a kin to the Pope</hi> in his poynt of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> affirme it to be in the very <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>moment</hi> or <hi>instant</hi> of the souls <hi>departure,</hi> which is not <hi>in tempore</hi> it seems, not in any time at all, but <hi>in instanti,</hi> and so sith <hi>Instans non est Tempus,</hi> but as it were <hi>punctum temporis,</hi> the instant being but a poynt of time and not <hi>properly Time it self;</hi> it seems that</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Accidit in puncto quod non speratur in aevo.</head>
               <p>That happens in a <hi>poynt of time,</hi> which could never be so much as hoped to he attained in all the <hi>life time</hi> before.</p>
               <p>Thus the Divines <hi>dance</hi> between this <hi>world and that to come,</hi> not knowing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95242:9"/> yet where <hi>Purgatory</hi> is, nor daring to say <hi>distinctly one thing</hi> nor <hi>other,</hi> whether <hi>here</hi> or <hi>hereafter,</hi> in <hi>this World</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> hovering like <hi>Coesar at Rubicon</hi> with one <hi>foot</hi> over the dore <hi>sell</hi> t'other on <hi>this side, one in, t' other out▪</hi> one in <hi>that World,</hi> t'other <hi>in this World,</hi> saying with him yet <hi>I may go on,</hi> and when afraid, yet <hi>I may go back;</hi> So 'tis</p>
               <l>
                  <hi>Somtimes one way, then</hi> another,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Somtimes both wayes, this and</hi> t'other;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Somtimes one, o' th' two, take</hi> either,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Somtimes 'twixt both worlds, in</hi> neither;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some say 't's i' th' aire, some say 't's i' th</hi>' earth;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of knowledge where 'tis there's a</hi> dearth.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some say 't's here, there some, some</hi> (O Riddle)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor here, nor there, but just i' th</hi>' middle.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Contradictions,</hi> and <hi>various self-confutations, absurdities, riddles and rounds about their Rule of Scriptures.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>V. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o their <hi>Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> about▪ the Scripture</hi> or <hi>Letters,</hi> and not the <hi>spirit</hi> and <hi>lights</hi> being the <hi>Word of God,</hi> the <hi>fixt, firme foundation, stable standard, truest touchstone</hi> or <hi>tryall of all truth, only sure, inalterable, invariable, infallible Rule of holy life,</hi> They tell us <hi>one while</hi> not the <hi>light within,</hi> but the <hi>Hebrew and Greek Texts</hi> and <hi>Transcripts</hi> only, and those at least (though no <hi>Translations,</hi> but as agreeing therewith) are all those things abovesaid, that one only <hi>Lydius la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, unchangeable measure</hi> for all <hi>doctrines, spirits, faiths, truths,</hi> and <hi>things of God,</hi> and <hi>sayings</hi> to be measured by, yea both it self, and its own sayings also; the <hi>Word of God properly,</hi> the <hi>foundation, rule, inalterable</hi> and <hi>unaltered</hi> in so much as <hi>points, tittles, iota's,</hi> or losse of one <hi>letter</hi> or <hi>syllable,</hi> and what not? Quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the <hi>Qua:</hi> as siders with <hi>Papists</hi> in denying it only to be all this, and for calling it a <hi>nose of wax</hi> that is flexible, and may be twined and wrested by mistakes and mistranscriptions (as themselves confesse it may by many <hi>mistran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slations</hi>) and for calling it (as I. O. himself calls that most <hi>ancient Translation</hi> of it, the <hi>Septuagint</hi> (therefore see what an <hi>infallible rule</hi> and <hi>Word of God</hi> poor people have that know not <hi>Heb.</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi>) a <hi>Lesbian Rule,</hi> &amp;c. Witnesse I. O. whose businesse in all his Book above mentioned is to prosecute the proof of the Scripture in those and the like particulars, and T. D. in his Books, where he disputes the Scripture to be the Word of God, and only Rule of saith, and life, and that there's no other standing Rule but the Scriptures, p. 25, 26. 1 Pam. p. 16. 2. Pam.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles,</hi> yea no further off then in the self same Books wherein they prosecute the proof thereof, yea and T. D. no further off then in one of the self same <hi>pages,</hi> wherein he begins his discourse with me about it (<hi>to go round again</hi>) they plainly enough confesse the Scripture to be neither the <hi>Word of God</hi> nor the <hi>Rule,</hi> witnesse T. Ds. words, who, when told what the <hi>Scripture</hi> is, viz. a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>letter, writing</hi> that holy men wrote, replies <hi>you cannot think us so silly</hi> sure <hi>as to affirm the Scripture in that sence</hi> (which yet is the only sense in which it can <hi>properly</hi> be called <hi>Scripture) to be the Word of God, but we mean the matter contained in the Scripture</hi> (which is another matter then the Scripture) <hi>whether that be the Rule of faith or no:</hi> witnesse also I. O. who <hi>Ex.</hi> 15. 50. sayes <hi>Scriptura non verbum Dei vocatur formaliter quatenus scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95242:10"/> &amp;c. The <hi>Scripture formally considered</hi> (and if not so, not <hi>properly</hi> (say I) for <hi>forma dat esse, et est id per quam res est id quod est,</hi> is that by which every thing is what it is) <hi>is not called the</hi> Word of God. And yet (to go round again) p. 140. <hi>If the Scripture be what it reveals</hi> and <hi>declares it self to be, it is then unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionably the</hi> Word of the living God, <hi>for that it professeth of it self from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ending,</hi> and Exer. 1. S. 32. <hi>Scripturam saepius eo nomine a spiritu san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto indigitari cuivis eas vel leviter inspicienti facile apparebit;</hi> that <hi>the Scripture is very oft specially pointed out by that name is plain to him that but lightly looks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</hi> Exer. 1. S 28 <hi>Scriptura verbum Dei est, locis poene innumeris verbum Dei dicitur. The Scripture in well nigh innumerable places is called the</hi> Word of God, Joh. 17. 17. (a Text that <hi>vel leviter inspicienti</hi> touches on no such matter) and yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) in the self same Section, in the very next clause, for all those innumerable places (if there were, as there are not, so many in the book as the Scotchman said) ubi verbum Dei ennarratur promulgari, &amp;c. <hi>where</hi> the word of God is <hi>said to be preached, publisht, multiplyed, received, that most holy truth it self, which is in mens hearts,</hi> and is <hi>the matter of it, is, but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (formaliter) <hi>formally considered in no wise is intended:</hi> And yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) Exer. 1. S. 3. Fault is found with the <hi>Quakers</hi> by I. O. as meer feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from them of that <hi>verbum internum</hi> or <hi>inward word</hi> they talke of, because they do no more then I. O. does i. e. not own the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be intended in those well nigh <hi>innumerable places,</hi> but that <hi>holy matter, truth</hi> or <hi>Word</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture speaks of as nigh in the heart (of which I. O. himself Ex. 1. S 40. sayes also thus, <hi>verbum quod in nobis est;</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The word in us is that word of faith the Apostles preacht</hi>) Which <hi>well nigh innumerable places</hi> also I. O. himself sayes cannot be intended of <hi>Christs person</hi> neither, <hi>quoniam autem millies fere mentio facta est ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>because there is well nigh a thousand times mention made of the word of God, and its preaching, publishing, receiving, in those places which can't possibly be meant of the person of Christ and the Qua; will not acknowledge the Scripture as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended there neither, they carve from thence and wrest from thence I know not what Internall Word, of which they are possessors in chief</hi> &amp; Haeredes ex Asse <hi>of such as held it shut up among themselves of old:</hi> So shewing himself to be none of those Disciples of Christ, among whom his <hi>Testimony is bound,</hi> and <hi>his Law sealed up,</hi> and hasting in his haughty mind to quarrell with the <hi>Qua:</hi> for that which is no fault (unlesse it be his own also he proves himself to <hi>Haeres ex Asse illorum quos tenebrae antea inclusos tenuerunt,</hi> who were justly shut up in groapable dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse for despising the <hi>true light,</hi> so as to groap for the Wall like the blind, as if he had no eyes, to stumble at noon day as in the night, and, as one <hi>horrendo percussus scotomate,</hi> to run round with other <hi>blind guides</hi> in his <hi>giddy mind</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sense or reason so as not to feel when he <hi>interferes and hacks one leg against another,</hi> yea somtimes he confesses that the very <hi>Greek and Heb.</hi> copies or Transcripts are not only (as well as <hi>Translations</hi>) by the <hi>fallibility of the Scribes,</hi> and the <hi>Criticall faculties</hi> of men, liable to be turned eight wayes in one word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>some as contrary one to another as life to death,</hi> and what way any <hi>Critick</hi> will, and that the very <hi>immediate Transcribers</hi> of the <hi>Originalls,</hi> both <hi>might</hi> and also <hi>did erre, faile, mistake,</hi> and that thereupon <hi>various lections</hi> (when as I. O. at first said there was none at all, not in a Tittle) <hi>are risen</hi> (witnesse I. Os. own confession) and so not fit to be a <hi>foundation</hi> or a <hi>rule</hi> which (<hi>to goe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95242:10"/> round again</hi>) they say (witnesse R. B. I. T.) must <hi>not be variable;</hi> and those (though nickt in at next word by I. O. into the <hi>lesse offensive and formidable number</hi> of a <hi>few</hi>) yet at next word (<hi>to go round again</hi>) both clearly confest and plainly cleared by I. Os. own self, to be <hi>many,</hi> among which though I. O. at the next word <hi>nullifies</hi> them all under that <hi>diminutive</hi> name of <hi>A picular, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable accents not at all intren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hing on the sense, or at all of any moment,</hi> of no <hi>importance</hi>) yet some (<hi>to go round again</hi>) are confessed to be of <hi>some importance,</hi> and <hi>those of importance</hi> (quoth he) <hi>are considered by Glassius,</hi> and consisting not only in <hi>superfluity of words unnecessary, but in deficiency of words necessary to the sense of the places,</hi> and that some of them are of such moment as <hi>Textum sacrum et in literis et sensu corrigere,</hi> that they do alter the Text both in its letters and its sense: And though, to get from under that grievous ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h which this grant of his own gives to his <hi>grand assertion</hi> of no <hi>variation</hi> of the Text in Tittles, I. O. <hi>glazes</hi> it over with this <hi>glosse,</hi> viz. That those that are inconsistent with the sense in their stations, of more or lesse weight or moment are but <hi>private obscure</hi> and <hi>novell</hi> not <hi>above two or three hundred years standing,</hi> in <hi>some late,</hi> but no <hi>antient</hi> copies, yet by and by (<hi>to go round again</hi>) I. O. denyes not but that some are not only of such publick and open observation as to be obvious to the view of all, but also of long standing▪ witnesse his words, p. 190. <hi>There are</hi> (quoth he) <hi>in some Copies of the</hi> new Testament, <hi>and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se some of them of good Antiquity, diverse readings in things o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> words of lesse importance</hi> (and <hi>those which are of importance</hi> (quoth he p. 193.) <hi>have been already considered by others, specially Glassius, is acknowledged, the proof of it lyes within the reach of most in the Copies that we have, and I shall not sollicit the reputation of those who have afforded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> others out of their own private furniture,</hi> and pag. 27. of his Epist. he grants that there are <hi>Corruptions</hi> (mark) and <hi>various lections</hi> in the <hi>Greek Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies</hi> of the Scripture, and <hi>our grant</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>is founded on this experience, that we evidently find various lections in the</hi> Greek Copies <hi>we enjoy, and so grant that which</hi> ocular inspection <hi>evinces to be true:</hi> And though I. O. having yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Greek Text</hi> to be corrupted▪ which is enough to prove his foundation faulty and fallible, if the Hebrew Text were to a tittle entire) fills up that gap again with this <hi>fiddle-fadling defence</hi> (viz.) <hi>Yet there are none able to shew out of any Copies yet extant in the World, or that they can make appear ever to have have been extant, that ever there were any such</hi> various lections <hi>in the Originalls of the Old</hi> Testament: Neverthelesse (<hi>to go round again) notwithstanding what hath been spoken</hi> (quoth he, p. 178.) <hi>We grant that there are and have been va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious lections in the Old Testament and the New;</hi> and so falls a shewing in many pages together many varieties in the Old Testament himself, to save his Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonists the labour of shewing what he tells them they are not able to shew, some of which are not <hi>obscure</hi> and <hi>private</hi> (as I. O. sayes they are) but <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>open</hi> (as I. O. sayes) not (as I. O sayes they are) of no <hi>importance,</hi> but of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance,</hi> and <hi>inconsistent</hi> with the sence (as I. O. sayes <hi>to go round again</hi>) not <hi>novell,</hi> and of <hi>late</hi> only (as I. O. sayes they are) but (as I. O. sayes <hi>to go round again</hi>) of <hi>longer standing, of some good Antiquity:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I. O. all this while <hi>gives</hi> and <hi>takes, grants</hi> and <hi>begs back again, abates &amp; exacts the whole again, allows</hi> and <hi>pulls</hi> in again, <hi>owns</hi> and <hi>denyes, lets go</hi> and <hi>commands home</hi> again his Assertion, till <hi>by a little</hi> and <hi>a little</hi> he hath set it go, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95242:11"/> granted it all away, and then (<hi>to go round again</hi>) fearing he hath let it go too far from serving his turn, does what in him lyes (though <hi>hoc aliquid nihil est</hi>) by <hi>a little</hi> and <hi>a little</hi> to fetch it all in again to his first pretended purpose; he goes on <hi>granting</hi> from <hi>ore shooes</hi> to <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e boots,</hi> till in the <hi>quagmire,</hi> wherein he <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers too and fro</hi> in his <hi>quarrel</hi> for his <hi>quick-sandy foundation,</hi> he sinks first up to the <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kles,</hi> then up to the <hi>Knees,</hi> anon up to the <hi>Loynes,</hi> by and by up to the <hi>neck:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Lastly, searing lest he hath gone so far in <hi>granting</hi> to the weakening of his own <hi>Assertion</hi> of the <hi>Texts integrity</hi> to a <hi>tittle,</hi> that he shall hardly ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it to stand for truth in that <hi>exquisite primitive posture,</hi> wherein he at first <hi>exerted</hi> and <hi>propounded</hi> it, unlesse he utter somwhat more like a man, &amp; more to the purpose then all those <hi>childish pedling put offs,</hi> I. O. urges a <hi>knocking Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> from the multitude of the Copies to the <hi>impossibility</hi> of the Texts being corrupted, thus viz. p. 176. <hi>There was a multiplying of Copies to such a number that it was</hi> impossible <hi>any should corrupt them all willfully, or by negligence,</hi> which hath as much reason in it as his other <hi>confident conclusions</hi> have, for (<hi>Riddle</hi> me this, ye <hi>Rabbies</hi>) why might not the same fate fall out to <hi>one Copy</hi> of Scripture in its transcribing as to another? and if the sate and fault of <hi>falsity</hi> and <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake</hi> to some, why not to all? Yet if it were never such a solid consequence we need not deny it; I. O. (who still saves us the labour of confuting I. O.) knocks it down and confounds it himselfe, while elsewhere he argues from the multitude of <hi>Copies</hi> to the <hi>impossibillity</hi> of their esca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing corruptions; For (<hi>To go round again) That so many Transcriptions</hi> (quoth he) <hi>should be made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some variation</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is, <hi>impossible;</hi> thus running out in hast to recover his lost <hi>Assertion,</hi> he runs himselfe or'e head and eares in the Gulf of most <hi>irreconcileable contradiction, and irrecoverable confusion;</hi> yea, how many <hi>various Lections</hi> and <hi>various contradictions</hi> to himself, are to be found (yet heres not all) in <hi>I. Os.</hi> opposing of that one plain undeniable truth; viz. That there are <hi>various Lections</hi> in the Copies of the very <hi>originall Texts</hi> of the Scripture which they call their <hi>Rule,</hi> which though they say tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (witnesse <hi>R. B. I. T:</hi> p. 43. &amp; 51.) <hi>That a Rule and guid should be certain, which will not deceive, and that which is variable and alterable cannot be a persons Rule, for it is the property of a Rule to be invariable, and the same at all times; the Rules, Measures, Weights, Dialls, Squares, and what other things are made, if they be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed they cease to be Rules, for Rules should be fized and certain,</hi> and confesse al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so with us▪ that <hi>Error minimus in principio fit major in medio maximus in fine,</hi> the least errour in a <hi>foundation</hi> makes a thing not fit to be a <hi>foundation,</hi> and so if the Scripture be not <hi>intire</hi> to a <hi>tittle,</hi> so but vel <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> one <hi>jot</hi> or <hi>tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> fail, and every letter be not preserved by Gods providence from being lost they must needs cry out <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> they have no footing nor foundation for their saith, <hi>and see no means of being delivered from utter uncertainty in and about all sacred truth,</hi> (Witnesse <hi>I. O.</hi> Ep: p. 25. and much more of that sort in his book, as its more at large talkt with, in the second of my four <hi>Exercitations</hi>) and do confesse also the Scripture is not only <hi>flexible</hi> and <hi>lyable</hi> to be changed easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at every <hi>Criticks will,</hi> and the <hi>Transcribers might and did fail and mistake, so that various Sections are thence arisen,</hi> witnesse I. O. p. 167. and Epist. p. 21, 22, 23, 24. where he tells how many wayes its easie for a <hi>Critick</hi> to alter it;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95242:11"/> Yet (<hi>To go round again</hi> and face about half way at least) they plead the said (<hi>confessedly) variable</hi> and much <hi>varied</hi> Text, to be the only <hi>fixt, firm, foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, sure Basis, stable Standard, right Rule, true Touchstone,</hi> and such like; Yea (and <hi>to go the whole round,</hi> and face quite about as they were) that it is neither so <hi>varied</hi> nor <hi>variable, by reason</hi> of the <hi>loving care and aspect of God over the Transcribers</hi> whom (yet for all that, he would not guid) <hi>infallibly, whose promise and providence</hi> which cannot <hi>fail, are engaged to preserve the</hi> Hebrew &amp; Greek Texts <hi>in their integrity to a tittle,</hi> but that its most fit to be own'd as the most perfect and only steady <hi>Rule and foundation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover how entirely true soever the <hi>Transriptions</hi> are, the <hi>Translations,</hi> which is all the <hi>Rule</hi> the people have (unlesse the Priests prattle must be their <hi>Rule</hi>) are confessed to be most <hi>various,</hi> and <hi>abominably,</hi> and <hi>wofully corrupted;</hi> Witnesse I. O. who is scarce more busie to evince the <hi>entirenesse</hi> of his <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek Text,</hi> then in <hi>evidencing the erroneousnesse of all Translations,</hi> some of which that are most <hi>ancient</hi> and of most account among most Priests (as the <hi>Septuagint</hi> are gone off (quoth I. O.) <hi>from the Original in a thousand places twice told.</hi> And yet (<hi>To go round again</hi>) the only <hi>infallible Rule</hi> and <hi>sure Word of God</hi> which they tell the poor people that they have, is the <hi>Scripture Text,</hi> as it is thus <hi>Translated,</hi> for they to them either the <hi>infallibility</hi> of their own <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry,</hi> or of the <hi>Holy Chair,</hi> and any <hi>present guidance</hi> of any by the <hi>Infallible Spirit</hi> also.</p>
               <p>Thus they run the <hi>Rounds, trace to and fro,</hi> and <hi>dance up</hi> and <hi>down</hi> in their <hi>darkminds</hi> about the <hi>transcriptions and translations</hi> of their <hi>Text,</hi> which they take to be their <hi>Rule</hi> which <hi>transcriptions</hi> &amp; <hi>translaions</hi> were they never so certain and entire by answering to the first <hi>originall copies,</hi> yet are not <hi>capable</hi> to be (to all men) any other then a <hi>lesbian Rule</hi> or <hi>Nose of Wax,</hi> forasmuch as even where men have them as halfe the world has not they are liable to be wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sled, and actually <hi>twisted twenty</hi> wayes by <hi>interpretours,</hi> whose <hi>expositions, senses</hi> and <hi>meanings,</hi> which are as <hi>many</hi> and <hi>various,</hi> as the <hi>thoughts,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits,</hi> and <hi>inventions,</hi> of the men are who <hi>comment</hi> upon them, must be the <hi>Rule</hi> to such as can read them neither in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> nor in their own <hi>Mother-Tongues</hi> neither: And whereas we ask them (who tell us that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>rightly interpreted</hi> only is the <hi>right rule</hi> of the faith by what <hi>Rule</hi> shall we know whether the <hi>Text</hi> be <hi>rightly interpreted</hi> yea or nay, and not rather wrested, and what is the Rule according to which men are to <hi>interpret</hi> that <hi>Rule of their faith,</hi> i. e. that <hi>Scripture (to go round again</hi>) they tell us the <hi>Analogy</hi> of <hi>Faith:</hi> And when we query how it may be known that that <hi>Faith</hi> is right according to which the <hi>Scripture</hi> is (if <hi>rightly</hi>) to be <hi>interpreted (To go round again</hi>) they tell us the <hi>Scripture rightly interpreted;</hi> And when we ask them how it may be known <hi>assuredly, uncontroleably, infallibly,</hi> that the Scripture is at all of <hi>God,</hi> and not a cunningly <hi>devised fable &amp; invention</hi> of men? they tell us by the <hi>Testimony of the Spirit,</hi> which (say they is <hi>necessary &amp; onely all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient to that purpose,</hi> [see the <hi>Articles of</hi> the <hi>Clergy of England</hi> about the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, And when we ask them but by what shall we try and find <hi>assuredly] in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly</hi> that that <hi>Spirit</hi> is of God, and not a false <hi>one</hi> that tells us the <hi>Scripture is of God; To go round again</hi>) they tell us by the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover as when others deny his <hi>asserted Authority, purity &amp; integrity</hi> of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95242:12"/> the <hi>Text, J. O.</hi> pleads it to the least tittle, and yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) falls flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to affirm the <hi>Non-integrity of it</hi> himself, so when he dreams those <hi>poor delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Fanatical souls</hi> (as he calls them call'd <hi>Qua:</hi> (who yet own it as <hi>usefull, helpfull, profitable, perfect</hi> to its own end <hi>through faith</hi> in the Light to the man of God) do deny the perfection of the Scripture to its proper end, then <hi>J. O.</hi> strikes up in such strict strains of proving the <hi>living power, efficacy, perfection</hi> of the said Scripture to its <hi>own proper end,</hi> which (he sayes) is the <hi>effecting</hi> and <hi>perfecting</hi> of mens <hi>eternall salvation without any help of the Spirit and Light within,</hi> stretching it out into such a <hi>singular absoluteness</hi> this way, as that which by it self alone is <hi>Regula perfectissima,</hi> Ex: 3. S. 26. <hi>ita perfecta,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus numer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> absoluta, ut nihil opus sit ulla alia revelatione per spiritum aut lumen internum,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>revelatio omni respectu perfecta,</hi> Ex: 3. S. 28. <hi>Potens servare animas, reslituens onimam, potentia Dei ad salutem,</hi> so that <hi>inania inutilia sunt alia omnia principia,</hi> &amp;c. S. 29. which all is more fully inculcated at large in <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>English,</hi> p, 83, 84, 85, 86, 87. where he sayes its <hi>absolutely call'd the power of God, and that to its proper end, the Rod of his power without other helps and advantages, that hath efficacy and power in it to save souls, living, effectual, sharper then any two edged sword,</hi> &amp;c. as Heb. 4. 12. and much more to that tune, adoring and extolling the external Text <hi>with the honour and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thats due to God, Christ and his Spirit, Light, and living word in the heart alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when <hi>J. O.</hi> comes to <hi>quarrel</hi> with those <hi>poor deluded souls,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> for the self same adoring and glorying in their enjoyment of the naked letter, and seeking for <hi>life</hi> and <hi>salvation</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> without the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Spirit within,</hi> which he and his Fellow-Scribes are found in, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the <hi>Qua:</hi> for at this day, as they were by <hi>Christ</hi> of old, and when he comes to <hi>quarrel</hi> with the <hi>Qua:</hi> for asserting that <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>Devills</hi> (as they call it) viz: <hi>Attainablenesse of perfect freedom &amp; salvation</hi> of the soul from sin in this life; then <hi>J. O.</hi> runs and rambles <hi>round about</hi> and <hi>about</hi> again with as great an Ardency as he danced the other way before, saying Ex: 3. S. 39. <hi>Falsissimum est sacram Scripturam, dum in hoc mundo Haeremus, respectu nostri totum suum finem obtinere aut obtinere posse; It's most false to say the Scripture or doth, or can obtain its whole end in respect of us while we live here;</hi> and if we ask where then does it do it in the world to come? no neither, then <hi>cessabit Scripturae usus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>its use will then cease, its accimmodated to our present state on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and if we ask does it do it at all? yes (quoth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or else it cant't he <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> as I assert it to be, for Ex: 3. S. 24. <hi>Disciplinae cujusvis perfectio,</hi> &amp;c. In English thus <hi>The perfection of every discipline stands in it's relation to its end, so as that is to be held perfect which can, and that imperfect which</hi> potis non est, <hi>cannot effect its own end, and the perfection of the Scripture, can consist in no other thing then its sufficiency to its own proper end, which is the perfecting our eternall salvation,</hi> which salvation though the Scripture be perfect, and does accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish it, yet (<hi>To go round again</hi>) it can accomplish it neither in this world, nor that to come, and so not at all; and (<hi>To go round again</hi>) is <hi>imperfect;</hi> and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet,</p>
               <p>That its not so <hi>absolutely perfect</hi> nor effectually powerfull to this end (of <hi>saving souls</hi> so as to <hi>need no other revelation</hi> by the Spirit or Light within, as he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95242:12"/> says 'tis, witnesse its inefficacy to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who are as busie in it to no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, as <hi>J. O.</hi> himself, of whom <hi>J. O. (to go round again</hi>) sayes p. 236. thus <hi>The Jews enjoy the letter of the Scriptures, yea they receive it sometimes with the honour and veneration due to God alone; Their poslession of it is not accompanied with the manifestation of the Spirit, without which as we see in the instance of themselves, the Word is a dead letter, of no efficacy for the good of souls, they have it for their further ruine, yea while they keep the Scripture</hi> (quoth <hi>J. O.</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and I of <hi>J. O.</hi> and such literal Christians as he is <hi>we shall never want wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons out of their own Armony for their destruction, like the Philistine, they carry the weapon that will serve to cut off their own heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, Though <hi>I. O.</hi> who sayes elsewhere, the <hi>Scripture is without need of other helps or advantages, or revelation by the Spirit, or Light within▪</hi> per se sola sufficiens) <hi>living, absolute, full of power and efficacy to save souls,</hi> and yet rides <hi>the Rounds</hi> so here, as to say that <hi>without the Spirit, the word</hi> (and that's more then the <hi>Qua:</hi> dare say, howbeit he means thereby but the <hi>Scripture</hi>) is a <hi>dead letter, of no efficacy to the good of souls,</hi> yet (<hi>horrendo percussus scotomate</hi>) he stayes not here, but having said the <hi>letter is dead,</hi> rather then the <hi>Qua:</hi> he so hates, shall be owned by him in saying the <hi>self-same</hi> that himself sayes, hee'l <hi>ride round back again</hi> to his first stage, that he may not seem to side with them, and therefore in Ex. 3. S. 40. where <hi>I. O.</hi> brings in the <hi>Qua:</hi> arguing strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against the <hi>Letters</hi> being the only most <hi>perfect rule,</hi> thus, <hi>Scriptura est litera mortua, Spiritus vivificat, quis literae mortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nisi ipse sit mortuus, adhaerere, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lit? The Scripture is a dead letter, the Spirit quickens, who but he thats dead will adhere to a dead letter as his Rule? I. O.</hi> brings in himself <hi>weakly</hi> answering thus, viz: (<hi>To go round again,</hi> to the confounding of all his own former sayings that the <hi>letter is dead) Falsissima est ista assertio, Scriptura est verbum Dei quod vivum est et efficax ne{que} us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam litera esse mortua dicitur;</hi> i. e. <hi>That's a most false assertion, the Scripture is that word of God which is living and efficacious, neither</hi> (quoth he, <hi>Trapezuntius</hi> like who forgot his <hi>own name,</hi> forgetting its the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>I. Os.</hi> own imposing in the same book) <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the letter any where at all said to be dead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>J. Os. Rounds, and Contradictions to himselfe about the Hebrew punctation.</head>
               <p>Moreover as to <hi>Hebrew Points J. O. capers</hi> about, <hi>quavers</hi> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and down, and <hi>runs round like</hi> a blind Horse in a Mill; <hi>One while</hi> asserting them <hi>coaevous with the Consonants,</hi> of such <hi>necessity</hi> that without the owning of these to be of <hi>Divine original men are left</hi> (which is as much as to say all the <hi>Iewish Church</hi> were so left from <hi>Moses</hi> to <hi>Ezra,</hi> if the Points were added, but by <hi>Ezra</hi> and his <hi>companions,</hi> and not by <hi>Moses</hi> at the first writing) <hi>unto great uncertainty in all Translations and Expositions of the Scripture,</hi> p. 202. That who owns them not <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s so,</hi> and are otherwise minded then those who maintain the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the <hi>Vowels</hi> and <hi>Accents,</hi> so as that the <hi>Hebrew Language</hi> was written with them from the beginning, not only make doubtfull the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures, but even pluck it up by the Roots, sith without the Vowels and Notes of distinction, it hath nothing firm and certain,</hi> p. 2. 13. <hi>That he that reads it without Points (as the Church did before Ezra, if Ezra</hi> was the first Author of them) <hi>is as one that rides a Horse without a bridle, that may be carried he knows not wither,</hi> whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on relating the opinion of <hi>Radul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h Cevall,</hi> to be that the <hi>Hebrew Language was plainly written with them from the beginning; This mans judgement</hi> (quoth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95242:13"/>
                  <hi>I. O.) is also mine;</hi> yea p. 205, 207. He makes <hi>the foundation of all Questionable upon the supposition of the Novelty of the Hebrew Points,</hi> insinuating it as a <hi>just consequence which great and wise men suppose naturally, and necessarily flows from the opinion of the Novelty of the Vowels, and from the state of the Hebrew Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and Bible unpointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles</hi> notwithstanding, not knowing whether he had best assert them to be so ancient or no, he (<hi>to go round again</hi>) at first faces <hi>halfe about,</hi> and leaves those, who held them up as high as <hi>Moses,</hi> to prove it, saying on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>He shall not oppose them that maintain the Points Coaevous with the letters,</hi> and yet after a while does no less in effect then <hi>face quite Round about,</hi> and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose them in the same sentence, by this confident assertion; viz. <hi>I no wayes doubt but, as we now enjoy them, we shall manifest that they were compleated by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> The men of the great Synagogue, Ezra and his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> p. 210, 211. and p. 226. Pleading against such as hold them to be more <hi>Novel,</hi> and of no higher invention, then from the <hi>Tiberian Missorites,</hi> on his own, and their behalf, who affirm <hi>Ezra and his companions</hi> to have been the <hi>Authors</hi> of the Points, he sayes their sayings, whom he opposes, <hi>cast a probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that</hi> Ezra <hi>laying aside the old letters because of their difficulty, together with the new introduced the Points, to facilitate their use;</hi> which, if so, then he leaves all ages of the Jewish <hi>Church</hi> before <hi>Ezra,</hi> even the true Saints, meerly for want of the <hi>Hebrew Vowels and Accents,</hi> as men <hi>riding Horses without Bridlès, who were carried they knew not whether,</hi> but so the <hi>Saints</hi> then were not, and though the generality of the <hi>Jews</hi> were, yet 'twas not because they had no <hi>Vowels, Accents, and Points</hi> to attend to as their guides (though I am of <hi>J. Os.</hi> mind, tis like they then, and till <hi>Ezra's</hi> days had none) but because they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be led <hi>by the Light within,</hi> and guided by the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> which, for all their attendance to the letter, they (as <hi>Stephen</hi> said Acts 7.) had allwayes resisted.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>I. O.</hi> to the <hi>contradiction</hi> of his <hi>first-selfe,</hi> is <hi>run round down the hill</hi> from <hi>Moses</hi> as low as <hi>Esdras</hi> about his <hi>punctilio's,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew Points,</hi> but there he reckons to stand and keep his ground against all that come against him, to bring him and his <hi>Ancient rich possession</hi> of <hi>Pins and Points</hi> any lower, or at least so low as the <hi>Tiberian Massorites:</hi> and here he fights like a man in a <hi>fright</hi> or <hi>frensie,</hi> lest <hi>all truth be for ever lost, if he can't make it uncontroleably manifest</hi> that the Points are <hi>better guides then may be expected</hi> from such bad men, as the <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berian Massorites;</hi> And first to make that good, to the begetting of an <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible,</hi> and <hi>divine faith of the Points divine original,</hi> and not such a <hi>humane</hi> one as they must have, if from the <hi>Massorites,</hi> that these <hi>Charecters</hi> the Hebrew Points (mark, <hi>as we have them</hi>) are not to be ascribed to the <hi>Massorites</hi> as their <hi>Authors,</hi> he does not more make severall <hi>silly consequences,</hi> then he does him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <hi>confound them,</hi> even as fast as he makes them.</p>
               <p>First (Not to meddle here with those many <hi>paedantick proofs and put offs,</hi> which I have elsewhere (viz: in the 2 Exer: of my Book call'd <hi>The Country correcting the Ʋniversity,</hi> sufficiently already disproved) he treats it out throw a great part of his two Treatises with no other <hi>Tool</hi> then that <hi>Toy of Tradition,</hi> or a <hi>taedious, vain, uncertain talking</hi> of some <hi>Learned Humanists, Iews</hi> and <hi>Christians,</hi> in proof of the <hi>Points original</hi> before the <hi>Massorites,</hi> against
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95242:13"/> othersome, full as <hi>well-studied</hi> as the other, and in an <hi>extravagant</hi> way <hi>Argles</hi> against the <hi>Arguments</hi> urged by not only learned <hi>Iews,</hi> and <hi>Iesuites, Elias Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Bellarminus,</hi> &amp;c. but also confessedly learned Protestants, <hi>Luther, Zwinglius, Prideaux, Capellus</hi> against his <hi>pretended antiquity</hi> of the Points from <hi>Ezra,</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garying abroad unreasonably in the high <hi>Road of forgeries and fables, then which</hi> (as he sayes himself, p. 264.) <hi>in nothing more hath the world been chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> answering <hi>conjecture</hi> with no more then <hi>conjecture,</hi> laying about him like a <hi>Thatcher,</hi> thawcking <hi>Author</hi> upon <hi>Author story</hi> upon <hi>story, tittle</hi> upon <hi>tattle, fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> upon <hi>fancy, humane fallible persuasion against humane fallible perswasion,</hi> and yet in his conclusion not only shooting a thousand years short of <hi>Moses,</hi> from whom he would at first have drawn them, but also not <hi>adventuring</hi> to <hi>vent</hi> himself about their compleat <hi>being</hi> and <hi>beginning</hi> from <hi>Ezra</hi> at any <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> or <hi>clearly,</hi> but thus <hi>cloudily</hi> only, viz: <hi>Let any man judge whether from such a heap of uncertainties any thing can arise that may be admitted to give testimony in the cause in hand,</hi> and so say I, either for or against, on <hi>one</hi> side or '<hi>tother;</hi> for <hi>quod utrobi{que} incertum est, non est vel hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vel illinc certum,</hi> whats <hi>uncertain</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two, concludes nothing either way for <hi>certain</hi> and so he falls as short of making it evident that they were first from <hi>Ezra,</hi> as they do who say they were at first from the <hi>Massorites</hi> or <hi>Jewish R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bbins:</hi> But suppose his <hi>argument</hi> from the <hi>tradition</hi> of some men, had been as 'tis not) from all <hi>men downwards (Nemine contradicente,</hi> none to <hi>vye,</hi> with the rest) if he go about thereby to manifest, as he does, the undoubtednesse of his consequence and conclusion, yet he hath confounded it himself, if no other man had ever stirred against the businesse, whilest (<hi>to go romnd again</hi>) he tells us p. 105. <hi>The constant Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of more then a thousand years, carried on by innumerable multitudes of men, great, wise, and sober from one generation to another, doth but set open the gates of Hell for Mahumetans as well, to prove the goodnesse of their Alcoran,</hi> and p. 107, 108. Because this <hi>Tradition</hi> is pretended with great confidence, as a sure bottome &amp; <hi>foundation</hi> for <hi>receiving</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> (&amp; in effect so 'tis say I by I. O. for the receiving the <hi>Points</hi> from <hi>Ezra,</hi> not the <hi>Massorites,</hi> and that not without the <hi>Tradition</hi> of as learned to <hi>vye</hi> with the <hi>Reporters</hi>) I shall (quoth he) a little further inquire into it. <hi>Tradition, which is report of men, from those who are gone before may be either of all men of the world, or only of some of them, if of all, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their suffr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges must be taken in some convention, or gathered up from the indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals, as we are able and have opportunity, if the first way of receiving them were possible, which is the utmost improvement that imagination can give the authority inquired after, yet every individual of men being a lyar, the whole Convention must be of the same complexion, and so not be able to yield a sufficient Basis to build a faith upon,</hi> cui non potest subesse falsum, <hi>that is in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>allible, and cannot possibly be deceived, much lesse is there any foundation for it in such a report, as is the emergency of the Assertion of individuals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I. O. with the <hi>whirlwind</hi> of his own <hi>round about</hi> doctrine, layes all his long <hi>Traditionary Tales</hi> for the <hi>Antiquity of his tittles</hi> on the ground again, with his own <hi>talk</hi> of the <hi>invalidity of Tradition</hi> to beget such a <hi>divine, infallible faith,</hi> and <hi>certainty,</hi> as men must have about the Scripture▪ which he makes the <hi>Rule, Basis</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of all <hi>faith and certainty,</hi> in other things; so</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diruit, aedificat, mutat quadrata Rotundis.</head>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95242:14"/>
               <p>Secondly I. O. treats out two more Arguments for the <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of his <hi>tittles,</hi> whereof if no man should intermeddle to confute them) the one confounds and utterly overturns the other.</p>
               <p>The first, whereby (<hi>Alas poor man</hi> he hampers himself (and to as little ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) most horribly to evince the Points to be as high as <hi>Ezra</hi> at least▪ which salves not his <hi>Assertion</hi> of the <hi>Texts integrity</hi> however, were it granted him) and not so <hi>novel an invention</hi> as of the <hi>Tiberian Massorites,</hi> is an <hi>extraordinary excentrick bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndlesly bitter</hi> invective, as against the <hi>Iewes</hi> in general, in their rancor against <hi>Christ,</hi> wickedly attempting the <hi>restoration</hi> of their <hi>Religion</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Barchochab</hi> and <hi>Rabbi Iuda,</hi> by the compiling of their <hi>Talmuds,</hi> and much other <hi>impertinent staffe, and story,</hi> of which I. O. himself very truly consesses, p. 234. in <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tidem verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that its all nothing to his own purpose,</hi> so specially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Tiberian Massorites</hi> in particular, the supposed <hi>Authors</hi> of the <hi>Heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rew Pun ation</hi> for half a hundred pages together; not caring how he vilifies them, so he may but bring men to beleeve so badly of them, as not to own them as the <hi>Inventors</hi> of the <hi>Vowels</hi> and <hi>Accents,</hi> but <hi>Ezra</hi> or some holy men guided therein at least by the <hi>infallible direction of the Holy Spirit:</hi> His Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he hath from Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> drawn close up out of p. 240, 241, 242, 246, 247. in form is on this wise, <hi>The pointing of the Bible savours of the work of the Holy Spirit, not of wicked, blind, mad men,</hi> but the <hi>Tiberian Massorites were wicked, blind, mad men, possessors of the Letter without the Spirit, desperately enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to oppose the truth, under Gods curse, one of whose funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals was opposition to the Gospel, feeding themselves with vain fables,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">True Characters all along of our present Priesthood, and Schoolmen, &amp; Universities, <hi>De quibus haec fabula vere narratur.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>and mischievaus devices against the Gospel, labouring to set up a new Religion under the name of the old, in despite of God, so striving to wrestle it out with his curse to the utmost, men of a profound ignorance in all lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and knowledge, but what concerns their own dunghill Traditions, and innumerable fopperies, addicted to such mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous fopperies as their Successors in after ages are asham'd of, and seek to palliate what they are able, Idolaters crafty, raging, serious in nothing, childish about serious things, how much deceitfulness, froth, venome, smo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k, nothing in their disputations;</hi> Therefore, considering the <hi>importance</hi> of the <hi>Hebrew Vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and Accents</hi> to a <hi>Right understanding of the Scripture,</hi> we need clear, yea <hi>undeniable, unquestionable evidence and testimony</hi> [and so (say I) there is as <hi>clear,</hi> and <hi>unquestionable</hi> given this way, as I O. who is concerned to give <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> proof his way, gives to the contrary] <hi>to prove the Rise and Spring of the Points to be from these men, that is, the</hi> Tiberian Massorites.</p>
               <p>This is one of I. Os. Arguments, which how it lacks little confutation by any thing, but its own apparent <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>evident weaknesle</hi> and <hi>blindnesse,</hi> a child may see: It intimates <hi>as if wicked men</hi> could not <hi>possibly</hi> find out and affix fuch a thing as the <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>Accents, Vowels</hi> and <hi>Points,</hi> to facilitate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the reading of any <hi>Character</hi> whatsoever, as if it must be some more then or inary <hi>divine</hi> and Supernatural <hi>work</hi> to devise the shape of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Vowels,</hi> more then 'tis for the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>English,</hi> or others to devise theirs; whereas, if I. O. had not for hast run himself out of the Remembrance of things that are so obvious and ordinary that none but <hi>Ignoramus</hi> and <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zuntius</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:95242:14"/> himself could easily forget them, what more common and frequent then for men that are <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>enmity</hi> against God to have the skill and faculty of inventing not only <hi>tittles, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cents, points and vowels,</hi> but also <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Consonants,</hi> and <hi>Characters, Figures,</hi> and those of diverse sorts and shapes, long and short hand to expresse themselves by in writing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinting in their respective native <hi>Languages:</hi> I trow who invented <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and our <hi>aeiou,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ai oi eu ou,</hi> and the several kinds of figures for different sounds, and what Nation hath not some of that wit that <hi>England</hi> hath so much of, as to find out many sorts of <hi>Chirography</hi> and <hi>Brachography</hi> for their own conveniences? and who invented first that so great, so skilful, so useful and eminent work of <hi>Typography</hi> it selfe, &amp; so many exact wayes of cutting and setting, and stamping so many different <hi>Characters</hi> of all Languages? might it not be done by men who heeded not the <hi>inspirations</hi> of the Spirit? by men moved meerly with love of mony, and hope of gain? in which way the <hi>Bible</hi> comes out lyable to the common sate of all other Books, as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>falsification</hi> by <hi>misprinting?</hi> How many differing Characters and sorts and sizes of Letters, of <hi>Greek, Hebrew, English</hi> are, and have our <hi>Bibles</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves been written and printed in? and doth not I. O. himself p. 227. tell us of an <hi>universal Character</hi> attempted by diverse, and ready to be brought forth by his Dr. <hi>Wilk: Ward,</hi> whereby to expresse all his <hi>Apert, Simple,</hi> and <hi>Double sounds, Vowels</hi> and <hi>Dipthongs,</hi> which I. O. says, will doubtlesse give <hi>universal satisfaction</hi> to <hi>learned</hi> and prudent men, when he shall communicate his thoughts on it? and yet I. O. denyes <hi>Wilkins Ward,</hi> or any man else in these dayes to be <hi>inspired</hi> or <hi>guided by the infallible Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How worthlesse and frivolous then? what childishnesse, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? what <hi>froth, smoake, nothing</hi> are the thoughts of I. O. and his <hi>Co-Conjecturor</hi> Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> whom he there cites, p. 247. who can scarce beleeve it possible that the Points should <hi>hominem sapere,</hi> proceed from such a School as the <hi>Tiberian Ʋniversity,</hi> or savour of the work of any <hi>Humanists</hi> or wicked men, or of any other then the <hi>Spirit of God?</hi> But if this Argument of I. O. had any such force in it as were worth reselling (as indeed it hath not) yet, if we should say nothing to it, I. O. <hi>backs</hi> it with another so strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he breaks the very <hi>back</hi> of this, so that it can bear nothing of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den he layes on it, nor be of the least <hi>import,</hi> whilest after all his talk of the wickednesse of these men, in proof of their <hi>unfitnesse</hi> and <hi>unlikelinesse</hi> to be the <hi>Authors</hi> of such a businesse as the Points, least this should fail (<hi>To go round again still</hi>) he adds this as another <hi>Argument</hi> thereof, viz: <hi>The likelinesse of it that there were never any such men as these</hi> Massorites <hi>in the world at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>odde</hi> and <hi>Antick</hi> is I. Os. extream eagernesse in driving on his design against them that talk of the <hi>Tiberians,</hi> as the <hi>Authors</hi> of his <hi>Superlatively prized Points,</hi> that rather then any should imagine those men to have invented them, he streins and stretches his <hi>twatling strings</hi> so far, as not to deny, but own, and tell us 1. that there was an <hi>Ʋniversity</hi> and <hi>School</hi> of such <hi>Tiberians,</hi> and so describes the men who and what they were, and when they liv'd (<hi>viz:</hi>) after the finishing of the last <hi>Talmud,</hi> p. 240 241, 242. Only that they were men <hi>so, and so, and so ill mannered and qualified, Idolate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Magicians,</hi> &amp;c. and what not that's evill? as not likely to be <hi>Inventors of so rare a businesse as Vowels
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95242:15"/> and Accents.</hi> Secondly, Lest all this should not be of force enough, next by a denyall of it to fright souls into a faith and fancy that there were <hi>never any such men in the world at all;</hi> to which purpose he uses such <hi>suppositive, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> &amp; <hi>negative</hi> expressions concerning it, as whereby to cause it to become <hi>questionable</hi> and render it <hi>doubtfull</hi> whether there ever were any such, or nay, <hi>Men they were</hi> (quoth he) (<hi>if any such were) who were so and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o,▪</hi> 240. and 243. <hi>Of all the Fables that are in the Talmud, I know no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e more incredible then thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> story</hi> (quoth he) <hi>that men who cannot b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y any story</hi> [Mark, he sayes, it appears not by any story there were such, and yet in the very line above sayes 'tis a story in the <hi>Talmud;</hi> Was there ever any man found so self-<hi>confounding</hi> in a Treatise as I. O. and so ready in this work of running the Rounds?] <hi>or other record be made to appear that they ever were</hi> in rerum natura, <hi>not obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, not taken notice of by any learned man, Jew or Christian, should find out so great, so excellent a work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which (say I) That though of all the Contradictions that I. O. gives to himself, this is not the first, nor greatest, nor clearest, to say as he does p. 246. &amp; 247. that learned Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> observes and takes notice of the <hi>Ʋniversity and School at Tiberias, and of the great Doctors</hi> among the <hi>Tiberia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> by name out of the <hi>Talmud</hi> (viz:) <hi>R. Juda, R. Chanina, R. Chaija Barba, R. Jochannan, R. Jonath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Rabbins, Gem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rists, and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes,</hi> of whom I. O. sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es the Jewes generally beleeve not only that there were such men, but also that the Points had a reviving by them according to the observation and notice of <hi>R. Az<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rias,</hi> and yet p. 243. to say, as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oes, that it cannot be made to appear by any story or other <hi>Record,</hi> that ever there were such, and that they are unobserved, and not taken notice of by any learned man, <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Christian;</hi> yet of all the ridiculous passages that are in the <hi>Talmudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al</hi> Treatise of I. O. this is not the least not to say the most incredible) that men of whom it cannot by any story or other record be made to appear that they ever were in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> should according to, or by I. Os. strange story of them, be made to appear to any reasonable man to be Idolaters, Magicians, wicked, blind and mad men, &amp;c. Surely they must first appear and be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be in <hi>rerum naturâ,</hi> before they can to or by any (save such blind Seers as can see nothing at all better then they can see things as they are) appear &amp; be observed, much more described by name to be in <hi>natura hominum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>npro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borū,</hi> and if any man beleeve with I. O. that those men can appear to him to be wicked men, &amp;c. <hi>In esse cognoscibili,</hi> who cannot be made to appear at all that they ever were at all in <hi>esse re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li;</hi> Il'e give them leave to upraid me with [<hi>O thou of little faith, wherefore dost thou doubt it?</hi>] for my beleevable faculty is indeed too narrow to entertain, or contain that self-gainsaying story for a truth: <hi>Credat Apella:</hi> he that can beleeve it let him, I am an Infidel as to that foolish figment, and if these two contrary Tales can be both true, my reason can't reach the reason of these <hi>Rabbinical-riddles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But among the numerous odd passages that passe from I. O. in this Point about the proof of the Points antiquity, that which is yet more observable, as to my present purpose is, that I. O. when he hath roled <hi>Sysiphus</hi> his stone a great while, <hi>perve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ire ad summum,</hi> to get up to the top, to prove the pedigree of his <hi>Punctation</hi> as high as <hi>Moses</hi> if it might be, if not, from <hi>Ezra</hi> at least, seeing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95242:15"/> he could not hold it up in the utmost hight, nor carry it clearly into a <hi>coae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vousnesse</hi> with the <hi>Scripture,</hi> according to the strictnesse of his <hi>position,</hi> conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scends to come down by the <hi>Rounds</hi> of his Ladder half way, first to the dayes of <hi>Ezra,</hi> and in the prosecution of his undertaking to manifest it (as at first he makes no doubt to do) that they were <hi>compleated by Ezra</hi> and his <hi>Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> finding himself uncapable to carry the matter, against such as derive their descent from the <hi>Judaical Rabbins,</hi> or <hi>Tiberian M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>slorites,</hi> clearly up so high as <hi>Ezra,</hi> but only <hi>cloudily</hi> by foisting, flinging, and casting out at least but <hi>forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> against <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgery, fable</hi> against <hi>fable,</hi> and a heap of uncertainties against the heap of uncertainties of others, for so he will needs call the most cogent and more then probable evidences of all his confessedly learned Antagonists, <hi>Elias, Capellus, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther, Prideaux,</hi> &amp;c. p. 218. 264. 267. Though his own pleas, considerations, repulses and replyes, are in the eyes of all impartial ones (suppose I should say (but as) 'twere enough, <hi>ad hominem,</hi> to impeach his position of utter falshood, though I might say more) uncertain, at last he sinks down by the <hi>Rounds</hi> as low as the <hi>Massorites</hi> dayes, and so <hi>per force</hi> by little and little yeilds up as far as is demanded from him, assenting with <hi>Azarias</hi> p. 247. <hi>That the Jews generally beleeve these Points to have been from Moses, at least fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Ezra, not denying t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at the use and knowledge of them, received a great reviving by the Gemarists</hi> and <hi>Massorites, when they had been much dissused,</hi> and p. 271. with the same <hi>Azarias</hi> ascribing them <hi>as to their virtue and force,</hi> to <hi>Moses,</hi> or <hi>God</hi> on <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> as to their <hi>Figure</hi> and <hi>Character,</hi> to <hi>Ezra,</hi> as to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ration of their use, unto the Maslorites,</hi> in which he hath come quite Round with much ado▪ and granted enough to prejudice his own position, to the utter overthrow of the truth thereof, for as to the <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>force,</hi> none can deny them to be <hi>coaevous</hi> with the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Language it selfe▪ but 'tis the <hi>Figure</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> only the question is about, and that is yeelded to be but from <hi>Ezra,</hi> and since <hi>Ezra</hi> to <hi>have been much diss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sed,</hi> but to have received their great <hi>Reviving and Restoration</hi> to the use they now stand in (which is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing pleaded for against I. O.▪ from the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssorites,</hi> and so howbeit I. O▪ makes <hi>no doubt,</hi> p. 211. <hi>but to manifest it that they were</hi> (as we now enjoy them) <hi>compleated by Ezra and his companions,</hi> yet instead thereof he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed in effect that (as we now enjoy them, since last dissused) they were <hi>revived, restored, and compleated</hi> by the <hi>Massorites,</hi> whom he disclaims as having any hand in them. There remain sundry more <hi>Contradictions</hi> and <hi>Rounds</hi> I. O. runs in about the Points, of which for a tast take one more here (though touched on elsewhere) and then (<hi>sat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod suffocat</hi>) as more then enough from I. O. so enough from me, as to that <hi>point</hi> of the <hi>Hebrew Punctation.</hi> P. 217. <hi>I shall manifest</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>that its fit they,</hi> i. e. the Points, <hi>should be all taken out of the way, if they have the Original assigned to them by the</hi> Prolegomena, <hi>i. e.</hi> from the Massorites; Yet p. 221. <hi>Grant</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>the Points to have the Original pretended; yet (to go round again) they deserve all regard and are of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular use for the right understanding of the Scripture, so that its not lawfull to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from them without urgent necessi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> &amp;c. Yet p. 244. (to go round again, and face quite about as ye were <hi>I professe</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>if I could be throwly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that the present Hebrew Punctation were the figment and invention of those men,</hi> i. e. the Massorites, <hi>I should labour to the utmost, to have it utterly taken away
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95242:16"/> out of the Bible, nor should I in its present station make use of it any more, to have it placed in the Bible as so great a part of the Word of God is not tolerable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contradictions and Rounds of I. O. about the manner of the first giving out of the Scripture.</head>
               <p>P. 10. 153. The <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>come forth</hi> (mark) unto us from God, <hi>without the least mixture or interveniency of</hi> any medium <hi>obnoxious to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llibillity (as is the wisdome, truth, integrity, knowledge, memo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of the best of all men (or capable of giving change, or alteration to the least Iota or Syllable:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet</hi> p. 30. (to go round again) <hi>We live</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>many yeares from the last person who received any part of the Scripture from God, &amp; have not received it</hi> immediately <hi>from God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So p. 5, speaking of the first Penmen of the Scripture, <hi>Their tongue</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>in what they spake, or their hand in what they wrote, was no more at their own disposall, then the pen is in the hand of an expert writer.</hi> Yet p. 6. (to go round againe) <hi>their mind</hi> (quoth I. O.) <hi>and understanding was used in the choyce of words, for they did use</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> words of choyce. Yet Ex. 1. S. 29. <hi>Verba disposita sunt per spiritum sanctum, ne{que} ad exprimendum sensum quem ipsi de mente et voluntate Dei conceperunt ingenio ac arbitrio ipsorum scriptorum sunt permissa aut relicta</hi> (To go round about as ye were) <hi>The words were at the disposall of the holy Spirit, neither to expresse the sense they conceived of the mind and will of God, were they lest to the dispose, arbitriment, will, or choyce of the Writers themselves:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, as I. O. so abundantly (as is above shewed) <hi>contradicts</hi> and <hi>confounds</hi> himself in many matters about the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or <hi>outward Text,</hi> so about the sence and meaning of <hi>one Text</hi> of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> wherein they all 4 disagree with the <hi>Qua:</hi> I. <hi>Os.</hi> hand, like <hi>Ishmaels,</hi> is against all his fellows hands &amp; every of his 3 fellow fighters hands (whom I have here to do with, who from the same Text fence against the <hi>Quakers</hi>) is against him to the <hi>confounding</hi> of him: which Text is Ioh. 1. 9. Where <hi>the true light</hi> is said <hi>to enlighten</hi> every man <hi>coming into the World;</hi> for howbeit I. O. <hi>cloudily concludes</hi> with all the other three, viz. T. D. R. B. I. T. in concluding and crouding that most <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall Terme <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, every man,</hi> within the little compasse and narrow corner of his <hi>wheel</hi> in a <hi>wheel,</hi> i. e. The <hi>Elect men</hi> only, saying <hi>Synagogically</hi> with the rest, <hi>Hoc est Syncategorema istud</hi> omnis, <hi>non absolute sed relate ad Electos dicitur,</hi> This is the <hi>Consignification of that Term</hi> [All] <hi>its meant not absolutely, but relatively to the Elect;</hi> yet when he sayes <hi>Non dicitur Christum illuminare omnem hominem venientem in mundum, sed quod ipse veniens in mundum omnem hominem illuminat, Christ is not said to enlighten every man that comes into the World, but that he coming into the world lighteneth every man,</hi> and that this is the sence of those words (the falsenesse &amp; silliness of which <hi>sence,</hi> &amp; the <hi>insufficiency</hi> &amp; <hi>nothingness</hi> of it also to serve his turn against the <hi>Qua:</hi> (if granted him) I have shewed in the book it self, to which this is but an <hi>Appendix</hi>) Here not only each of his three friends forsake him (for T. D. himself among all his many meanings meddles not with this) but two of them viz. I. T. and R. B. who <hi>backs</hi> I. <hi>Ts.</hi> Book, make bold to fight against him for it as well as the <hi>Qua.</hi> do; Witnesse their words, p. 1, 2. <hi>There is a doubt whether it should be read thus, that was the true light coming into the World, which inlightneth</hi> every man, by a trajection, or (as ours read it as the words are placed) <hi>That was the true light which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95242:16"/> every man which cometh into the World.</hi> Grotius after Cyrill, and Austin and some others (see how the <hi>Divines</hi> are <hi>divided,</hi> and the <hi>Founders confounded</hi> among themselves) <hi>likes the formar as best; but first such trajection disordering the words, 2. The phrase being as fitly interpreted of birth as of appearing as a Teacher, I rather chuse the reading of our Translators, And</hi> p. 24. <hi>They tell us over again how, coming into the World here is related to every man coming, and not to Christs</hi> coming <hi>into it,</hi> and how they before gave reasons against I. <hi>Os.</hi> sence.</p>
               <p>So having been walking the <hi>Rounds</hi> with these men to give the World a <hi>Review</hi> of the <hi>Riddles</hi> they are wrapt in, and the manifold <hi>Contradictions</hi> they are by the <hi>network</hi> of their own hands <hi>snared, catcht</hi> and <hi>tangled</hi> in about their <hi>letter,</hi> till I am come with them to that main <hi>Text</hi> at which they leave me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it talks so plainly of the <hi>true light</hi> which they love not, and I leave them to <hi>dance</hi> about still in the <hi>darknesse</hi> of their own <hi>divinations;</hi> I proceed (in the light in which I see them, though they, being out of it see not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves) to open briefly to <hi>all people,</hi> who love not to live with them rather in their darknesse, then in <hi>Christs light,</hi> the <hi>mist of darknesss,</hi> wherein they <hi>mop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> about, and <hi>dance the Rounds</hi> in their <hi>discourses</hi> about the <hi>Light,</hi> in their fiery fluttering against which, the <hi>wicked</hi> now is as he ever was, snared in the <hi>work of his own hands,</hi> Psal. 9: 16. <hi>Higgaion, Selah,</hi> consider and note it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contradictions, Absurdities, and Rounds concerning the Light in the Conscience, which the Qua: testifie to.</head>
               <p>As concerning the <hi>True Light</hi> or <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>Gods grace in every man,</hi> the four men aforesaid do (as all their fellowes do <hi>uno ore) babble</hi> somwhat about it, and bear <hi>witnesse</hi> either <hi>for</hi> or <hi>against</hi> it, but <hi>each mans</hi> witness agrees no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter together within it self, then that they give about the other matters abovesaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Somtimes</hi> they call it Light, <hi>truly▪ really, naturally</hi> and <hi>properly</hi> so, and not <hi>metaphorically,</hi> nor by way of <hi>allusion</hi> to what is so: Witnesse I. O. p. 74. <hi>It is spirituall, morall, intellectuall</hi> light <hi>that hath the preheminence as to a participation of the</hi> nature and properties of Light. <hi>Otherwhiles</hi> the same who excluded it from the name of <hi>Metaphoricall,</hi> by that of <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>proper (to go round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain</hi>) do conclude it to be <hi>metaphoricall,</hi> as in opposition &amp; contradistinction to both <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>proper;</hi> Witnesse I. O. who confounds his own foresaid saying, p. 74. with another division Ex. 3. S. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, &amp;c. Where under that same term of <hi>metaphoricall</hi> he distinguishes that <hi>Light</hi> he calls <hi>morall, spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, intellectuall</hi> (as respecting and exercising mens <hi>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds</hi> whether in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>morall, civill</hi> or <hi>spirituall</hi>) from that which respects <hi>bodily sight,</hi> which he call'd <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>proper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Somtimes they call this very light, whereby duties and <hi>divine things</hi> are discerned, <hi>universall</hi> and <hi>common to all</hi> (as the <hi>Qua;</hi> do i. e. in some measure, though not to all in the same) but when so, then no other but <hi>naturall,</hi> as in opposition to <hi>supernaturall</hi> and <hi>spirituall;</hi> Witnesse T. D. p. 1. 1 pamp. <hi>Naturall and supernaturall light are two, and though all have the one, yet few the other,</hi> and I. O. Ex. 4. S. 17. <hi>Lumen internum omnibus commune naturale est,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The light within common to all is naturall,</hi> and to be called so, S. 18. <hi>If this light that is</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon▪
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95242:17"/>
                  <hi>be not</hi> naturall, <hi>the very Intellect is not</hi> naturall. So S. 25. <hi>Concessimus reliquias primaevae lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is esse in omnibus, sed eas esse</hi> spirituales <hi>id pernegamus, some relicks of the primitive light we grant to be in all, but deny these to be</hi> spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: <hi>Nihil non naturale, nihil spirituale communicatum &amp;c. Nothing but what's</hi> narurall, <hi>nothing thats</hi> spirituall is common or communicated to all: So also R. Bax. I. Tom. A naturall <hi>light from Christ is yielded to be in every</hi> man, &amp;c. pag. 33.</p>
               <p>Otherwhiles this very <hi>universall</hi> light in all which before was said to be not <hi>supernaturall</hi> or <hi>spirituall,</hi> but <hi>meerly naturall (to go round again</hi>) is by these men yielded to be at least <hi>more</hi> then <hi>naturall,</hi> and so no lesse (according to T. <hi>Ds.</hi> division of light into two) then <hi>supernaturall</hi> and <hi>spirituall:</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse (against themselves) R. B. I. T. p. 37. <hi>It can hardly be avouched that that knowledge in morality and divinity which they</hi> (i. e. <hi>People that never had the Law nor Gospell made known to them as the</hi> Jewes <hi>and</hi> Christians <hi>have h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d) attained to, was by meer light of</hi> Nature, and in Baxters Epistle, p. 7. he tells us of a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ommon supernaturall light</hi> given to the <hi>unsanctified.</hi> I might also call in <hi>John Horn,</hi> and the two <hi>Thomas Moores</hi> that push with him against the truth, as Witnesses of the same confusion that is among all the Priests in this matter, who in their book stiled, <hi>A fuller Discovery,</hi> &amp;c. P. 61. affirm the light where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Christ lighteth <hi>every man</hi> is both <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>spirituall;</hi> but as my busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse lyes mainly with the other four men; So <hi>George Whitehead</hi> hath suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enly thrust down the vain thoughts already of those three, in his Book stil'd The <hi>Hee goats Horn</hi> broken: So I let them passe. Witnesse also T. D. who, though he (together with I. O. p. 77. Nor doth it in the lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t impair this self-evidencing efficacy of the Scripture that it is a <hi>morall</hi> and <hi>spirituall</hi> not a <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> light) owns the <hi>Scripture,</hi> specially the light in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> or <hi>holy matter</hi> contained in the <hi>Scripture</hi> to be a <hi>morall, spirituall, supernaturall,</hi> and not a <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Rule</hi> or <hi>Light,</hi> yet affirms it to be <hi>common</hi> or <hi>universall▪</hi> i. e. in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the hearts of all, even the very Heathen, p. 16. 2. pamp. <hi>The matter contained in the Scripture</hi> (quoth he) <hi>is a Rule to all men (so far as tis revealed to them) and was so before 'twas put into writing, and so much of it as is written upon the hearts of the Heathens is a Rule to them,</hi> Rom. 2. 12. Thus T. D. who before made the one light to be Two, viz. <hi>Naturall</hi> and <hi>supernaturall,</hi> here (<hi>to go round again</hi>) makes that <hi>light</hi> which is in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and in the <hi>Heathens hearts,</hi> Rom. 2. 12. truly One and the same, and no lesse then <hi>supernaturall</hi> and <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall:</hi> Witnesse also I. O. who calls the light often <hi>naturall,</hi> yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) Ex. 4. S. 9. <hi>Splits</hi> this <hi>one light,</hi> which they all somtimes falsly call no more then <hi>naturall,</hi> into a <hi>Light</hi> which is both <hi>naturall, civill, supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> and <hi>spirituall,</hi> as it were all at once: <hi>This Light</hi> (quoth he) <hi>or faculty of understanding</hi> (so he foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lux autem haec seu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligendi facultas, in eam quae maere</hi> natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis <hi>est, eam{que} quae circa res</hi> civiles <hi>versatur▪ at{que} illam quae res</hi> spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ales <hi>omnia{que} alia in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad finem</hi> superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalem, spiritualem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ultimum <hi>discernit, disp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>scitur: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lumen au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> internum</hi> spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuale, <hi>seu facultas intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendi <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, varium &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> calls it) <hi>splits it self into</hi> meerly naturall, and civill, and supernaturall, i. e. spirituall which <hi>diseerns</hi> spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <hi>matters, and all things in order to the last end,</hi> and this inward <hi>spirituall light</hi> (quoth he) <hi>or faculty of understanding spirituall things spiritually</hi> is various, &amp;c. Where note how I. O. (falsely) calls the light no
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95242:17"/> other then the <hi>faculty</hi> of <hi>understanding</hi> which he calls elsewhere (truly enough) but <hi>naturall</hi> and yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) calls the very <hi>faculty of understanding</hi> which is common to all men, as men, by the Title of this <hi>inward spirituall light</hi> which discerns <hi>spirituell</hi> things and that <hi>spiritually,</hi> in order to the <hi>supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> and <hi>ultimate end,</hi> i. e. Salvation. And this inward <hi>spirituall</hi> light <hi>common</hi> to all that discerns <hi>spirituall</hi> things <hi>spiritually</hi> in order to that <hi>ultimate end,</hi> I. O. sayes is various too, and very well he may (if it may be divided again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those two severall sorts into which I. O. <hi>sub-splits</hi> it) for whereas here he calls this <hi>Light</hi> in the Conscience which the Qua. call to) <hi>lumen internum spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuale</hi> &amp;c. An inward <hi>spirituall</hi> light, which discerns <hi>spirituall things spiritually</hi> in order to the <hi>supernaturall, spirituall</hi> and <hi>ultimate</hi> end; yet a little lower, viz. S. 17. (<hi>to go round again</hi>) he calls it meer <hi>darknesse</hi> it self, by which no <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine saving</hi> thing can be seen; witnesse his words, * <hi>This Light within common to all, however attended to,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lumen hoc internum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus commune, utcun{que} ei attendatur, non est ullo respectu salutare, sed in rebus omnibus divinis, finem ultimum quod atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, merae tenebrae et cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas.</note>
                  <hi>is</hi> (quoth he) <hi>in no respect saving, but in all divine matters, so far as to the ultimate end,</hi> meer darknesse and blindnesse:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>One while</hi> again they deny this light to be the <hi>visive</hi> (i. e. <hi>Intellective) faculty</hi> or <hi>eye</hi> of the soul, or to be given for any such end, as so much as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the desect of the <hi>visive faculty:</hi> Witnesse I. O p. 77. <hi>Light will not remove the defect of the visive fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty: Light is not eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles (to go round again</hi>) It is the very <hi>visive faculty</hi> as Ex. 4. S. 9. <hi>This light or faculty of understanding, which is meerly</hi> naturall, &amp;c. <hi>This inward</hi> spirituall light <hi>or faculty of understanding spirituall things spiritually,</hi> &amp;c. So S. 8. 18. Lux quae proprie mentem respicit seu facultas illa intelligendi est <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; oculus, acies mentis, <hi>The light which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly respects the mind, or the faculty of the understanding, is the sight, the visive force, the very eye of the mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>One while</hi> they tell us that its true among the <hi>Gentile Philosophers</hi> there was <hi>light</hi> that guided well, and that in the Law there was light, and <hi>that no light that is truly such</hi> (though <hi>dimme</hi> and imperfect, as (say they) that of the <hi>Philosophers</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> was) <hi>is to be rejected,</hi> Witnesse R. B. I. T. p. 68.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles</hi> some <hi>light,</hi> yea even the <hi>Philosophers light,</hi> which led them well (as they say afore) in some, did in most things <hi>lead men into crooked <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd dangerous wayes:</hi> therefore, unlesse men love, and it be best to be led into <hi>crooked</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> wayes (to <hi>go round again to be rejected:</hi> Witnesse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst themselves, R. B. &amp; I. T. in the self same page, the next line but one after the other, witnesse also I. O. against them both, who Ex 3. S. 28. sayes of the <hi>spirit</hi> and <hi>light</hi> within the <hi>Qua:</hi> calls to (among other things that he calls <hi>incerta, periculosa, inutilia minime necessaria, re<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>cienda,</hi> at{que} <hi>detestanda</hi>) that they are to be both <hi>rejected</hi> and <hi>detested.</hi> Thus when they begin of their own accord among their own supposed friends <hi>somtimes,</hi> these men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95242:18"/> and extoll, and call men to <hi>heed</hi> this <hi>light</hi> in the Conscience, which the <hi>Qua:</hi> call to, so <hi>eminently</hi> that the Qua: scarce need more words to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to men in, as to its <hi>excellency, divinity, usefullnesse, profitablenesse, needfullnesse, and necessity</hi> to be heeded and obeyed, then the same which our <hi>Divines</hi> themselves, who hate it, do seem to set it out in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otherwhiles,</hi> that is, when any <hi>Qua;</hi> begin to <hi>call men</hi> to it, to <hi>commend</hi> and <hi>extoll</hi> it among their Parish people (though in their own forms of speech a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it) and when the <hi>Qua:</hi> desire them, as they will prove themselves true <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> to labour to turn all men to <hi>the light within</hi> themselves; then (<hi>to go round again</hi>) either they'l be silent, or (if they <hi>sing</hi> any thing at all concerning it) <hi>sing out</hi> no more so loudly as before to the <hi>praise</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of it, but rathe (what they are able, they <hi>sing</hi> their <hi>old new song,</hi> to the <hi>Turncoats Tune</hi> of <hi>Truth turned out of Doores</hi>) in way of <hi>dispraise</hi> and <hi>dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> and utter <hi>detestation</hi> of it to the utmost, as if twere the vilest kind of <hi>Canting</hi> in the whole world to utter one word in order to the begetting of any people into so much as any measure of any good <hi>opinion</hi> at all of a light within, so that I may truly say of these <hi>Seers</hi> as the <hi>Poet</hi> once of one of <hi>Caesars Singers:</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Omnibus hoc vitium est cantoribus inter amicos,</l>
                  <l>Ʋt nunquam inducunt animum cantare rogati,</l>
                  <l>Injussi nunquam desistunt, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <p>To shew the World how <hi>Sepharically</hi> these <hi>Ministers</hi> sing out the <hi>high praises</hi> of the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>light</hi> of the World, the <hi>light</hi> in the <hi>Conscience,</hi> when they please to begin of themselves. and (<hi>to go round again</hi>) how <hi>symphonically</hi> they set it at their heels, in opposition to the <hi>Qua:</hi> rather then the <hi>Qua:</hi> shall prevail with them to say any thing of it that is any better then nought, I shall hereunder shew both their <hi>voluntary calls to,</hi> and <hi>commendations▪</hi> of, &amp; their unjustly occasioned <hi>cautions</hi> about &amp; <hi>condemnations</hi> of this light of <hi>Christ</hi> in the Conscience of men, when the <hi>Qua:</hi> commend and call to it, and set the one of these <hi>immediately</hi> under the other, only premising this, that whether they speak of the <hi>light</hi> which themselves call <hi>Christs,</hi> which the letter holds forth and testifies to, or the light wherewith God shines and shews his will and mind in some measure in the hearts and minds of all men, even Heathen Philosophers or others, which we call Christs light, though they do not we mean (however they divide these) no other but that one Law of God which the Letter is the Copy of, which is <hi>spirituall, holy, just</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> which T. D. confesses to be the <hi>Heathens Rule</hi> so far as is w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itten in their hearts. <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of the World, and his <hi>light</hi> in the heart, which the Scripture testisies of abundantly, &amp; not any such thing as mans own thoughts, <hi>wisdome, imaginations, inventions,</hi> &amp;c. Which the Heathen became <hi>vain</hi> in, Rom, 1. which the <hi>Qua:</hi> call all men out of, and the Divines, that lead men by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are themselves yet led by more then any, steering by nothing but their own many m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds and meanings on the Scripture, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Some few calls to, and Commendations of the light, with Cautions to take heed to it, collected out of many more that are in R. B.</hi> and <hi>I. T. his Book.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <q>P. 68. It concerns us, (say they) to take heed how we dote on our own
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95242:18"/> reason, or the most exact writers of morality, and neglect the light which Christ hath brought into the World: Let us be wise so to use Candles as not to burn day▪ light, that we so make use of all the reason &amp; humane wisdome and virtue we have our selves, or discern in others writings or examples that yet we chiefly eye and follow the grand light, the Sun of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, the Lord Jesus, learning him by studying the great Counsell of God, which he revealed and denying our selves take up our Crosse and sollow him as his Disciples; Christ is to be chosen and followed as our Light: An Exhortation to use Christ as our Light, that was the true Light which lighteth every man that cometh into the World; be induced to imbrace and follow the Lord Christ as the great Light of the World, besides the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence out of Scripture to prove him to be sent from God a <hi>light</hi> into the World, &amp;c. His sayings and doings do amply confirm it.</q> And p. 88. 89. they go on thus; <q>Though the Jewes contradicted and blasphemed, the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperour raged, <hi>Lucian</hi> jeered, <hi>Liba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ius</hi> wrangled, <hi>Julian</hi> calumniated, Papists, corrupt Gn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sticks, Hereticks, Fanaticks, Quakers,</q> [<hi>here they abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably bely the truth, for the</hi> Quakers <hi>call all and only to the light of Christ</hi>] <q>adulterate and cloud the truth of Christ, they do but pisse against the Sun, the light of Christ Doctrine, the truth of the Gospell doth and will shine forth, nor can all the cavills (<hi>say they</hi>) of moderne Atheists, or the dust raised by new Phantasticks, take away the brightnesse of Christs light, or hinder its enlightning others then themselves, and shall we after all the Arguments given of Christs being the true light, follow after <hi>ignes fatuos,</hi>
                  </q>
                  <hi>[who these be but that fraternity, who would have men follow their fancies, and not Christs light in the Conscience, which is that the Quakers call to, I know not</hi>] <q>What reall comfort or spirituall help to holinesse or heavenly directions do they give to lead men to God, better then Christ hath done? May you not discern a vain glorious spirit, a self-seeking, proud, carnall spirit in them, what do their censures of others shew, but a mind to extoll themselves? their affected speech, looks, carriage, but a desire to hide their falshood? what do all the devices of Iesuits, Popes, and their Agents tend to, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by force or subtlety to set up the monstrous powers of the man of sin, and their own domineering over mens consciences under him?</q> [<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>actenus recte quidem sed et etiam de te fabula O Parochialis Sacerdos</hi>] <q>What is in their conclave but pollicy? in their counsell but deceit? in their Iesuists and Casuists but jugglihg? shall we go after such Masters and leave Christ? Remember we that one is our Master, even Christ; when any shall sollicit us not to adhere to Christ as our Teacher, reject them: Christ hath warned you,</q> [<hi>say they, and so say I too as concerning any that lead forth from his light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, therefore, saith he, go not forth after them, nor follow them</hi>] <q>If any say low here is Christ or there</q> [<hi>and so do all Priests and Professors, and their Teachers in their sundry forms and outward observations, in which they look for the Kingdome which comes not in them</hi>] <q>believe it not. We will not venture our lives upon Mountebanks, and will we our souls upon deceivers? Shall we follow our own conceits, which often prove foolish, and neglect Christs Doctrine</q> [<hi>which say we still is his teaching light and counsell in the Conscience</hi>] <q>which alwayes proves wise and sase? no, no, let us answer as <hi>Peter,</hi> Lord, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95242:19"/> whom shall we go? thou hast the words of eternall life.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Alas, what can we expect but if we follow blind leaders, as all are that teach the things of God ortherwise then Christ and his Apostles did</q> [<hi>who, say I, called all along to walk in the light within</hi>] <q>we should fall with them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ditch, into everlasting perdition? On the otherside there is so much plain and clear light in Christs doctrine as will guide our feet in the way of peace; Away then with all such obtruded insinuating Teachers as indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to hide from us the light of Christ shining in his Doctrine, recorded in Scripture; Let's say <hi>none but Christ, none but Christ,</hi> that Christ which preached, dyed at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> that word of his which is written in my Bible</q> [<hi>of which the Bible testifies say I, that its near in the heart to heare and do it</hi>] <q>shall be my light: to the Testimony of Jesus</q> [<hi>which sayes the Scripture is the spirit of prophecy, the sure word of prophecy, that as a light shineth in the dark place of the heart, and is to be taken heed to</hi>] <q>to his Everlasting Gospell I stick.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>So <hi>Baxt.</hi> Ep. p. 7. (<hi>speaking of the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>;</hi>) Do they affirm that all men have the light of reason? who denyeth it of any but Idiots and Infants? Do they maintain that this light is from Iesus Christ, both as the Authour and restorer of nature? and by whom among us is this denyed? Do they say that repaired or reprived nature may be fitly called grace? about this also we have no mind to quarrell with them, so they will not exclude superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall grace thereby (<hi>as we do not, but hereby conclude it</hi>) Do they hold that common supernaturall light is given to many (at least) of the unsan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, &amp;c. and who contradicteth them in this? Do they hold that as the Sun is appointed in nature to be the light of every man that cometh into the World, though shutting our eyes may exclude it; So Christ is by office the Sun in the world of grace, giving men actually all the gracious light they have, being sufficient himself to enlighten all, and giving them an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating word, which is sufficient in its own kind to do its own part, though many are blind, and for their sin are deprived of the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this light? why all this we maintain as well as they: do they say that all this light (within us and without us) is to be hearkened to and obeyed? why what man did they ever speak with that's a Christian;</q> [<hi>no Christians indeed say I, but too many Antichristians</hi>] <q>that denyeth it?</q>
               </p>
               <p>[<hi>See what a deal of the Quakers doctrine concerning learning only at Christs light is here uttered by these men</hi> R. B. I. T. <hi>who yet hate the self same doctrine at their hearts when the Quakers teach it; olso in many other places they teach much more to the same purpose; putting men on to attendance to the light, yea even the light within every man,</hi> as P. 40, 41.] <q>This light usefull for two ends; First, To restrain men from excesse of sin, &amp;c. As he gave a Law to the <hi>Jewes</hi> because of transgression, to restrain them or abate punishments; so to other people he gave a law in themselves to prevent the extirpation of the Nations by bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling them in their lusts, thorow conscience of sin and fear of punishment. Secondly, Besides this God hath another end, that they might be inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable who sinned against the light in them, and God justified in his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and judgment upon them.</q> [<hi>Observe how this light within is owned by hem as the Law of God, which T. D. affirming the work of the Law only to be there,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95242:19"/> yet denyes to be in the heathens hearts, to the contradiction of these men and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self also in that other plaee,</hi> p. 16. 2. pamp. <hi>Where</hi> (to go round again) <hi>he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesses much of the holy matter of the Scripture to be written upon the hearts of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and that to be their Rule</hi>) I <hi>say as the Law of God which is spirituall, holy, just and good, and to be obeyed, for else transgression of it could not be sin deserving judgment, for sin is no other then the transgression of the Law.</hi>]</p>
               <p>So <hi>p.</hi> 82. 83. they go on thus, <q>If the light shine into thy soul from Christ so as any convictions or discoveryes of truth from Christ get into thee,</q> [<hi>and some convictions they confesle all have by the light within</hi>] <q>take heed thou hold it not in unrighteousnesse, nor seek to quench it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 18. Wrath to all that hold truth in unrighteousnesse, when lust imprisons light, no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance for the light of Christ into that soul, there must be a love of the light: Its the greatest sign of a man willfully evill, when he hates the light; and its a good sign of a man truly good, when he can delight in that light (<hi>mork</hi>) which discovers his own euills,</q> [<hi>What light is that which discovers a mans own evills but the light within? the letter without doth</hi> de jure <hi>only, the light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doth</hi> de facto <hi>discover mens own evill</hi>] <q>Christ hath determined this to be the great condemnation, that men love darknesse rather then light</q> [<hi>or else the Heathen could not be condemned, say I, who have and yet hate the light within, for they have no letter without</hi>] <q>for thats the sign they side with the Prince of darknesse, and men that do truth come to the light that their deeds may be manifest, &amp;c. The more light is rejected, the more purely voluntary any sin is, when men are willingly ignorant, they are incurably evill, &amp;c. Each person is to make their use of the light within him, so far as it is light and usefull. Certainly it concerns every man so far as to look to the light within him, (<hi>mark</hi>) that he do not, as tis said of some, Job 24. 13. Rebell against the Light,</q> [<hi>which Text in Job I. O. interprets of the letter, but I. T. to the confutation of I. O. (truly with us) of the Common light wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>in men</hi>] <q>A mens conscience is so far a law to him, that though it cannot of it self justifie</q> [<hi>which is contrary to</hi> Rom. 2. <hi>which sayes their inward thought as well excuses the Heathen when they do well, as accuses when they do ill, and excusation and justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or to excuse, clear, justifie are all one</hi>] <q>yet it may condemn him:</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So p, 37. they go on thus,</hi>
                  <q>God hath imprinted in all, even the most Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people, some relique of light, though in some it is so small</q> [<hi>that may be say we, for all have not the same, but all some measure of Gods light, which these men somtimes call darknesse, delusive and dangerous, and degrees vary not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the case</hi>] <q>that it can hardly be perceived whether there be any sense of sin or wrath, of duty or reward, of God or Devill, Heaven or Hell. Secondly, Some people that never had the Gospell nor the Law made known to them as the Jewes and Christians have had, yet have attained to so much knowledge and practice of morall duties</q> [<hi>Mark, morall duties are the main things of the Law, and required in the morall Law, viz. To do as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would be done by, which saith Christ is the Law and Prophets,</hi> Math. 7. <hi>The sunt, substance, and upshot of all, and more then all offering and sacrifice, so that the Jews failing in these weightiar matters, viz. Iudgment, mercy, faith, &amp;c. all outward oblations and observations were abhorred</hi>] <q>that in some acts of righteousnesse, temperance, chastity, fidelity, and such vertues they have equallized at
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95242:20"/> least in respect of their outward demeanour toward men, if not exceeded not only <hi>Jewes</hi>
                  </q> [<hi>who had the Scripture, as our Scribes have, and search, as much in it</hi>] <q>but also</q> [<hi>the more shame for the most of you filthy, fruitlesse, faithlesse Christians the while, whom very heathens will therefore judge</hi>] <q>the most Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Thirdly, And in the knowledge of God, though therein they were most defective, yet they attained to so much knowledge and right appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension of him, as enabled them to correct the Vulgar errours concerning God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>[<hi>See how far beyond our vulgar Christians, and very Christian Clergy men, that have the letter to boast, talk &amp; trade on, the light within hath led the very Ethnicks that have heeded it, by these mens own confession; But they go on yet further prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching up the light with the Qua: thus, p.</hi> 84. <q>It will concern those who own Christ as their light, to judge themselves and their wayes by his light:</q> [<hi>This act of self judgment is within saith I. O. Seconding that morall instinct of good and evill, that is imprinted by God on the Conscience from the innate light therein</hi>] <q>It is the great benefit of the light that it doth make manifest, Eph. 5. 13. Thus by the light of Christ the evill of our wayes is reproved, the wayes of God approved: Now this is no small benefit to have the light to discern our errors, which without light from Christ we should never have understood, A wise Christian will be often judging himself by the light of the Law, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his Transgressions</q> [<hi>That must needs be the Law in the Conscience which, de facto, shewes every mans own sins to himselfe</hi>] <q>It will be needfull not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to use the light of Christ to judge our selves by, but also to order our actions by. I am the light of the World, faith Christ, he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness. There cannot be unsafe walking by Christs light, there is no danger when Christ our light goes before, walk in the light saith Christ, while ye have the light, lest darknesse come upon you: how many millions a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> there of souls perplexed and tortured all their life with fears and doubts for want of walking by the light of Christ in Scripture</q> [<hi>which, say I, is that in the conscience which the Scripture mainly calls to</hi>] <q>and chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing rather to walk by a light and sparks of their own kindling</q> [<hi>alias their own wisdome, conceits, sences and meanings on the Scripture, traditions in worship, and such like which they call light</hi>] <q>which in the end either goes quite out, or burns so dim as to leave them in darknesse of spirit and horror of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and no marveile since such as neglect the word preached</q> [<hi>which is that word of faith i. e. which men are to beleeve in unto life, which the Scripture testifies, and the Apostles preached to be nigh in mens hearts to heare and do it</hi>] <q>should follow the mares of humane reason, the examples, customes, and dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of men, and in conclusionly down in sorrow, Isa. 40. 11. Such foolish fires will lead to nothing but bogs and precipices, but Christ the true light when his Gospell is followed (<hi>which is the light in the heart,</hi> 2 Cor; 4. 5, 6.) guides the feet of men into the way of peace: The light of Christ is to be used as our weapons or Tools to defend our selves, or to work with, let us put off the works of darknesse, and put on the armour of light, the truth is light, is the chiefest instrument for safety and worke, if a man be without light he can neither defend himself nor offend an enemy; he that would make use of Christs light must be armed with his doctrine; he that would
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95242:20"/> improve the light, must be a doing the businesse which the word of Christ directs him to, and to that end it (<hi>mark</hi>) must dwell richly in him. Make use of the light of Christ for thy comfort and rejoycing; it is it which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves doubts, griefs, fears, despair in life or death. Oh how sweetly might men live, how comfortably might they dye, if they did make use of it:</q> [<hi>Thus highly do these two men R. B. I. T. speake of the light of Christ within, which the Qua: preach: yea that in the very Heathen, though they oft call it naturall, yet they recommend it as that which told the truth to the heathen, which they holding in unrighteousnesse were under wrath, and without excuse before God, because they glorified him not as God, but were fill'd with unrighteousnesse, and did the things which by that of God in them they knew judgment was due to, and that they were worthy of wrath.</hi>] <q>Ignorance of the Law being not to be pleaded by them, (<hi>say they</hi>) who sin against the innate light of their own spirits, forasmuch as that fact must needs be voluntary which is done against the knowledge and judgment of a mans own conscience;</q> [<hi>And yet somttmes</hi> (to go round again) <hi>they tell us that when their Saints sin through infirmity only (as T. D. judges</hi> David <hi>did when he was guilty of murder and adultery) which when they doe they act against the knowledge and judgment of their own consciences, their facts are not voluntary, but altogether, yea utterly against their wills: Yea p. 41. They seem to judge themselves much belyed by the Qua. for denying the light within, and set themselves to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate themselves from that as a false aspersion, as if they were men that do truly own the light within as much as any, yea they there make a use of Application of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine about the Light that enlightneth every man that cometh into the World, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie themselves against the Qua: as owners and honourers of the light within, and to warn men that they act not against their Light within, to this purpose</hi>] <q>we may infer (<hi>say they</hi>) a plea for our selves against the unjust accusations of the Qua: who use to charge publick preachers with denying the light within each man, whereas such light is not at all denyed by them; each person is to make use of the <hi>light within,</hi> that he do not rebell against the light, a mans own conscience is a Law to him, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>[<hi>This and much more do these men, when they are pleased to begin of themselves confesse to the excellent usefullnesse and sing out to the praise of the light of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in each man, but if the Qua: fall in with them in the same work, and commend the same light (for tis no other but that of Christ the Qua: cry up) in the same words with the Priests, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in enmity against the Qua, they set themselves to cry it down with as much indignation and detestation, as they cryed it up with approbation and high commendation before: Then</hi> (to go round again) <hi>they sing a new song in contempt of it, to the Tune that hereunder followeth, inveighing most heavily and bitterly against the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k: for this businesse of warning men to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake heed to the Light within, to that of God in their consciences, calling both it and them no lesse then all to nought: witnesse their clamours against the Qua: for this very thing in</hi> Baxt. Epist. p. 7.] <q>Their i. e. the <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> great pretence, when they dishonour the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the Ministry, is to lead men to a light within them, and this is their cry in our Assemblies and our streets</q> [<hi>hearke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the light and word within you</hi>] <q>and the sufficiency of this they clamorously defend.</q> So <hi>p.</hi> 6. <q>They (<hi>i. e. the Quakers</hi>) assert that there is a light in every man sufficient to guide him to God of it self, that it is a Rule to shew duty and sin, that theres no need
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95242:21"/> of other teaching of man, that this is one in all, that it is the Gospell, this is the main prop of the new Anti-christian Religion, or frenzy of the <hi>Quak:</hi> and leads them into pernitious courses.</q>
               </p>
               <p>So p. 41. <q>A mans own light</q> [<hi>cry they, speaking of that of God in the Conscience of all men, which somtimes themselves call no lesse then Gods Law in them, which is in them, but not of them, nor naturall, but spirituall, holy, just and good</hi>] <q>cannot war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of it self without the Scripture a mans actions to be lawfull, which he doth according to that light</q> [<hi>And yet T. D. sayes much of the truth of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is written on the hearts of the Heathen, and that so much of it as is there written is their Rule, so by consequence mens Rule can't of it self warrant mens actions to be right that are regulated by it: (Oh the Rounds of these men) yea</hi> Tomb. <hi>and</hi> Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>blush not in proof of that their lye as boldly as blindly, to assert in the same page</hi> that <hi>Paul in his bloody persecutions and sins</hi> followed the light within him, and counted it his great sin <hi>that he had so done, though they confesse (as before) that all light in all men is from God and Christ, and that the light, some of which all men have from God and Christ, though dim in regard of its small measure, gives them to discern sins, dutyes, and divine Attributes, and leads them to much of God and more morallity, fidellity, chastity, temperance, righteousnesse, which the Letter sayes are the fruits of the Spirit, then most Christians have attained to: Yea so blasphemously seeme they to speak in the same page of the light within which the Qua. follow and call to, which is no other then that of God in men that convinces them of sin as to intimate that men may, as the Quakers say they do,</hi> follow the light within them, and yet their practice be of the Devill [<hi>The Prince and Ruler only of the darknesse in men</hi>] <q>and not from Gods Spirit, yea (<hi>say they there</hi>) if following the dictates of a mans own Conscience (i. e. <hi>the leadings of the light in it</hi>) could warrant his actions the most horrid acts of Idolaters, Papists, Pagans, Mahometans, Fanaticks, i. e. <hi>mad men</hi> should be free from censure and controul.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus to their own shame confusion, and self-contradiction who one while speak well of it, they speake abominably of the light within, as if all the wickednesle that is in the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame to passe by following the light within the conscience, the going away from which into mans own vain imaginations and vile inventions into the dark▪ &amp; not taking heed to the Councell of God, i. e. his light in the heart, is the only cause of all abomination, without which light shining, and mens loving the darknesle and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill deeds, which it condemns more then it, there could be neither sin, as Christ sayes, nor condemnation,</hi> Iohn 3. 19. Rom. 8, 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As</hi> (to go round again) <hi>to their own confutation themselves intimate in the very next words, p. 41, 42. which are thus.</hi>
                  <q>If a man do that which he thinks to be evill,</q> [<hi>that is by the lights dictating it so to be in his own Conscience, as they hinted just before</hi>] <q>though it were good and lawfull in it selfe, it would be sin to him, yea that man that doth good against his conscience is hut an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite in so doing, though the thing in if self be right and good: When a man doth evill, which his conscience tells him is so, he commits a sin of the highest degree, as to him that knowes to do good, and doth it not, to him it is sin, Iam. 4. 7. That is, sin in an high degree, hence great horrour of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath attended them that have omitted good, which their conscience told them they should do, and much more horrour in them that have done evill against their conscience, as in the case of <hi>Iudas, Spira</hi> and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ances
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95242:21"/> might be given</q> [<hi>Without which acting against conscience there's nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sin nor horrour say we with</hi> Iohn <hi>and Christ,</hi> Ioh. 15. 24. 1 Ioh. 3. 20. <hi>but peace as themselves hereunder confesse,</hi> i. e. <hi>assurance of Gods acceptance, acquittance, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemnation, justification.</hi>] <q>And therefore (<hi>say they</hi>) if the <hi>Qua:</hi> intended no more then this, by bidding men look to the light within them</q> [<hi>And no more then that do we intend, God knows, though the blind Guides, who can't see Wood for Trees, hating us, are minded to make men mistake us, as miserably as themselves mistake us</hi>] <q>that men should take heed that they omitted not the good their own consciences told them they ought to do, and that they did not the evill their consciences judged to be so, we should accept of their warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Surely it will concern you, as to look that your conscience be not er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneus</q> [<hi>As it ever is when, and never is, say I, but when it erres from the light of God within it, for the heart is a dark place of it self but as the true light shines in it,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 19. <hi>and heeds not that.</hi>] <q>So, when your conscience is rightly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to follow it, and when it goes wrong</q> [<hi>As it never does, say I, but when it goes from its guide the light</hi>] <q>yet to suspend the act which it condemns [<hi>Till by the light it come to approve of what it ignor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntly condemned</hi>] if you desire peace</q> [<hi>It seemes then by these men, as well as the</hi> Qua: <hi>do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine, that peace is no where to be had but in walking according to the light in the Conscience</hi>] there will (<hi>say they</hi>) <q>be no plea to acquit him before God, or to quiet his own spirit, who proceeds to act according to the light in his own conscience: And a sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the light of nature</q> [<hi>So they stile that voyce of God in the conscience still</hi>] <q>is so much the more damnable in that it is against the most irrefragable evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</q> [<hi>Mark how they somtimes yield the light in the conscience of all to be a far clearer evidence then that of the letter it self, and more dangerous to resist, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to which they somtimes (to go round again call the light within, but obscure, meer darknesse and blindnesle, and not so dangerous nor damnable to resist, but rather dangerous, yea no lesse then damnable to follow</hi>] He that doubteth (<hi>say they with Paul</hi>) is damned if he eat, because he eateth not of faith, for whatever is <q>not of faith is sin</q> (<hi>Mark how themselves affirme with Paul and us, that faith, without which nothing is pleasing to God, out of which all that's done is damning, to be a faith in that light of Christ, which is in the conscience. Wo be to him (cry they as we also do▪ who condemns himself in what he allowes, and contrariwise, say we and</hi> Paul, <hi>and consequently themselves, happy is he (and he only) who is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in himself (that is by the light in his own conscience) in what he allowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus absolutely do these Light-haters somtimes themselves blesse, approve and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the light, which other whiles they brawl and bark against, when its own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the</hi> Qua: <hi>appear to justifie it; Somtimes (to go round again) as absurdly do they bolt out bitternesse and hlasphemies against that light which (forgetting how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares they confesse the truth to the Qua:) otherwhiles they so eminently applauded as good and of God, &amp;c, making it somtimes pernitious, dangerous, yea in the highest degree damnable to neglect it; at othertimes (to go round again) pernitious, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and in the highest degree damnable to attend to it:</hi> As p. 68.] <q>Among the Gentile Philosophers there was light, but dim, no light, truly such, is to be rejected; Philosopphers light guided men well in some things; yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) in most did lead them into crooked and dangerous wayes</q> [<hi>Which position of these blind Guides is such an Ignis fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, such a</hi> Will <hi>with a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95242:22"/> wish or whimsicall piece of guidance, as they falsly render the light it self to be, which they call so; as if one and the same light of God should be a safe and sure guide at one time, and such a misleading, unsafe guide and foolish fire at another, as p. 84. w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll lead into nothing but Bags &amp; Praecipices, or as if the least measure of the light of God could lead any man into the least measure of iniquity; Yea somtimes they call this light of God in the Conscience, which is Gods own voyce (in Nature at least as I. O. sayes) his Law and most immediate Counsell to a man, no other then mans own counsell, way, lust that leads to cursing, Witnesse p. 45, 40. Where they say thus</hi>] <q>To leave a person to his own imagination, lust, to walk in his own counsell, his own way (which is all one as to leave him to the light within him) is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test curse and judgment to a man from God, for refusing to hearken to Gods voyce. Therefore the light within each person is of it self no safe guide, and the <hi>Qua;</hi> prescribe that to men as their rule, which God counts their curse</q> [<hi>yet (to go round again) p.</hi> 55.] <q>the light within each person is by creation and inward work of the Spirit</q> [<hi>So to be left to the inward work of the Spirit is it seems with these men the greatest curse, yet (to go round again</hi>) as <hi>before,</hi> p. 41.] <q>The <hi>Qua:</hi> charge publick preachers with denying the light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in each man, whereas such light is not at all denyed by them, but is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be a great benefit to mankind,</q> and p. 84. <q>It concerns those who own Christ as their l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght, to judge themselves and their wayes by his light,</q> [<hi>And the light within is his light,</hi> witnesse <hi>Baxt.</hi> Epist. <hi>above cited,</hi>
                  <q>This light is from Christ both as the Authour and Restorer of nature, all this light</q> (within us and without us) is to be hearkened to, and obeyed] <q>its the greatest benefit of light that it doth make manifest, by the light of Christ the evill of our wayes is reproved, the wayes of God approved, we know the righteousness of God and our own unrighteousness, this is no small benefit to have light to discern our own errours, which without light from Christ</q> [<hi>and his light within say I, by which only every man knowes, de facto, what he is</hi>] <q>we should never have understood, a wise Christian therefore will be often judging himselfe (<hi>And self judgment saith I. O. is from the light indelebly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted by God within each mans conscience</hi>) by the light of the Law</q> [<hi>Which law is light saith the letter,</hi> Prov. 6. 23.] <q>discovering his transgressions</q> [yet (<hi>to go round again</hi>) p. 85. <q>Oh that all that talk of the light within them would follow the light about them! Light within you whatever the <hi>Qua:</hi> tell you, will leave you in perplexity, when you shall have most need of comfort; but (<hi>to go round again</hi>) if you believe in the Light of Christ, as its held out to you in the Gospell</q> [<hi>That is the letter with them, which letter yet testifies the light of the Gospell▪ of Christ to be shining from God within mens hearts,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.] <q>you shall see the light of life. Therefore (<hi>to go round again</hi>) be perswaded</q> [<hi>Cry they, and so they conclude their Book</hi>] <q>to disclaime the pretended new light within you, as your sufficient guide to God, and chuse the light of Christ from Heaven in his Gospel to walk by</q> [<hi>Which Christ say I, speaks and shines from heaven to men, now no where immediately, but in mens hearts and consciences, though men write and speak as from him here on earth, whom speaking there by his spirit from heaven, it's more dangerous to turn away from, then from them that speak but on earth</hi>]<q> and it (<hi>say they and so say I</hi>) will guide and comfort you surely and sweetly to eternall life.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:95242:22"/>
               <p>So I have shewed how these two <hi>children of the night</hi> and <hi>darknesse</hi> R B. an I. T. who were wont to bite and tear one another about the Tradition of <hi>Infant Baptisme,</hi> do both concurr in their divinity doings against the <hi>Qua;</hi> and the light within, to bawl out somthing, <hi>uno ore,</hi> against both, far better then their <hi>joynt dis-joynted</hi> talk <hi>concurres</hi> together within it self; and so run the <hi>Rounds</hi> and <hi>dance</hi> the <hi>Hay,</hi> up and down, in and out, and somtimes <hi>round</hi> about, that the <hi>Reader</hi> of them can hardly discern or find whether they be fuller of <hi>concessions</hi> to the <hi>Qua:</hi> by their <hi>confessions</hi> to, and <hi>commendations</hi> of the <hi>light within,</hi> or of <hi>denyalls, contemnings</hi> and <hi>condemnations</hi> of it, for at severall times (somtimes more <hi>Expresly,</hi> somtimes more <hi>implicitly</hi>) they are found in both in a most egregious manner; <hi>One while</hi> (as if <hi>parturirent montes</hi>) mightily <hi>magnifying</hi> the light within for a great way together, as if we might warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably take them to be some <hi>trusty friends</hi> to it, <hi>Another while minifying, vilifying, nullifying</hi> it into nothing but some blind lump of darknesse; like the <hi>Lizard</hi> making many good prints upon it with their <hi>fore-feet,</hi> in that sandy way wherein they passe, and then dashing them all out again with a long <hi>bushy Tail,</hi> or Tale of it to the contrary; like the blind <hi>night B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> flying and fluttering up into the Air with a mighty <hi>humming noyse</hi> of <hi>Encomiums</hi> about it, and then dropping down into a piece of <hi>Cow dung:</hi> As the <hi>Devill</hi> serv'd him who is the <hi>Author</hi> of it, who, after he had set him upon the highest pinnacle of the <hi>Temple,</hi> he would fain have thrown down thence to destruction; so deal these by the <hi>inward light</hi> or Word of Gods speaking in the heart, which, after in <hi>words</hi> they with I. O. have <hi>magnified</hi> over all <hi>Gods name,</hi> they thrust it down (as he does) below every name yea and every thing almost that hath any <hi>name</hi> at all; and, as I. O. after in a <hi>sound of words,</hi> they have set it out as <hi>glorious,</hi> next to God, as the <hi>Sun</hi> in its brightnesse, render it under many reviling, opprobrious Titles, well nigh as odious, as <hi>Satan</hi> himself in his <hi>Princely,</hi> and their own <hi>Priestly</hi> blindnesse: So that which side soever of those two sides and sorts of say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or <hi>double tongu'd</hi> talk of the <hi>light</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> stands on, yet (unlesse <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictories</hi> can) it's certain all cannot be true which they utter of it: And if the <hi>worst</hi> should be <hi>true,</hi> as (<hi>absit blasphemia,</hi> far be it from any good man to beleeve their <hi>blasphemies</hi> of it are) then the <hi>best</hi> is false, and that at best proves themselves no better then <hi>Self confounders;</hi> but if the <hi>best</hi> they say of it be <hi>true</hi> (as most true it is) then R. B. and I. T. till they both repent in dust and ashes before the Lord for their sin in <hi>belying</hi> his <hi>light,</hi> can expect no better from him, then what is due to all <hi>blind Truth Blasphemers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for T. D. he sayes the least of all these sour in contradiction to himself about the light; howbeit, as is above shewed, not so <hi>little,</hi> but that its seen, that <hi>eodem cum illis haeret luto,</hi> he sticks in the same <hi>Quagmire</hi> together with them: But as for I. O he is more <hi>over head and eares</hi> in it, as to this poynt, then all the rest. I shall only take two or three more <hi>turns</hi> upon that <hi>wheel</hi> of his, on which he is unwearied in running round, and so make an end with them altogether at this time.</p>
               <p>And first <hi>let us see what</hi> I. <hi>O, saith by way of Concession to us, against himself, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the light in all mens conscionces.</hi> First, Tr, 1. c. 2. S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <hi>he writeth thus</hi> (viz.) <q>God declares his Soveraign power and Anthority, righteousness and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse by the innate or ingrasted light of nature, and principles of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of men. That indispensible morall obedience which he requireth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95242:23"/> of us as his creatures subject to his law, is in general thus made known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; <hi>Then citing and writing out at large that Text,</hi> Rom. 2. 14, 15. For the Gentiles, &amp;c. <hi>he goes on thus:</hi> By the light which God hath indelibly implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the minds of men accompanyed with a morall instinct of good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, seconded by that self judgment which he hath placed in us in reference to his own over us, he doth reveale himself unto the Sons of men</q> [<hi>And that we may know and be ascertained that this thing is no deceivable pretence, but that God doth so indeed reveale himself thereby he adds</hi> S. 13.] <q>The voice of God in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is effectuall; it declares it self to be from God by its own light and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. There is no need to convince a man by substantiall witnesses that what his conscience speaks it speaks from God, whether it bear testimony to the Being, Righteousness, Power, Omniscience or Holiness of God himself, or whether it call for that morall obedience which is eternally and indispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly due to him, and so shewes forth the work of the Law in the heart, it so speaks &amp; declares it self that without further evidence or reasoning, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the advantage of any considerations, but what are by it self supplyed,</q> [<hi>And then without an outward Ministry, letter, or writing surely, or if it did not, yet the letter without, that came from the light within, is of the lights own supplying</hi>] <q>it discovers its Author from whom it is, and in whose name it speaks: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, those common notions and generall presumptions of him &amp; his Authority, that are inlayed in the natures of rationall creatures by the hand of God to this end, that they might make a Revelation of him as to the purposes mentioned, are able to plead their Divine Original without the least contribution of strength or assistance from without</q> [<hi>Thus far I. O. writes the truth of the light within, saving here and there the interposition of that Epithite</hi> Naturall]</p>
               <p>Thus far have I set down I. <hi>Os.</hi> words, that all may see how far he accords with them in these words, in the same things about which he Quarrells with the <hi>Qua:</hi> as not knowing what to make of their Inward word and Light they talke of: which is indeed wholly (though himselfe sees it not) excepting in his often undervaluing of the <hi>Light within</hi> by that name of <hi>naturall,</hi> as in opposition to the <hi>Qua:</hi> which otherwise, while he sees it serves his turn so to do against another sort of his Antagonists, he magnifies in words, and makes as honourable with all his might, as the <hi>Qua:</hi> do, and together with them: He grants that its <hi>the voyce of God, a means of the knowledge of God, and of his will, of Divine Originall and Authority,</hi> calls for that <hi>morall obedience</hi> (A higher matter then he thinks for) <hi>which is eternally and indispensably due to God, speaks in the name of God and from God so infallibly in the heart, that it needs no other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, assistance, advantage, &amp;c.</hi> (and then not the letter) <hi>to witnesse that it speakes from God, is his law to which his creatures are to be subject, is ascertain'd to be no deceivable pretence, but that indeed by which God doth reveale himself to the soul of man, that light which God hath indelibly implanted in the minds of men, is accompanyed with a morall instinct of good and evill, seconded with a self-judgment in us in reference to Gods own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver us, shewes the work of the Law in the heart, so as they are left wholly inexcusable, who will not learn and know God from thence:</hi> neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse (<hi>to go round again</hi>) he pinches it back at first (after he hath done magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying it) with the diminitive termes of the Light of <hi>nature, low, dark, obscure, a winckling light, that scarcely peeps out of the most pernitious darknesse, enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95242:23"/> meerly in morall matters, duties, morall good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, sufficient to leave men without excuse, not save, nor bring them to the true knowledg of God, only that which was given to man at first before he fell, he state of the first man,</hi> and at last <hi>a thing altogether faigned, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable pretence, grossely imagined, every ones private light making as many Rules as men. That inward light, the Revelation that comes from which is uncertain, dangerous, unprofitable, no way necessary to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God and his will, therefore to be rejected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested. A means of the knowledge of God, and of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, boasted of by the Fanaticks, an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the written word of God which is most heavily damned by the Spirit of God, among that of confabula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Angells and others,</hi> id genus surfuris, <hi>of the like bran: that which we are sent to that we may get the knowledge of God, or any direction in our duty to him at no time and no where at all by God; a principle of Revelation most uncertain, fallacious, both as to it self, and what things it reveals; a meer faculty of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing; I know not what light, of no correspondency with the Scripture and word; I know not what divine soul of the world mingled in all things, which is Every thing, and truly Nothing; a light which, however atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to, is in all divine things, as to the utmost end, meerly darknesse and blindnesse it self.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These and many more <hi>Id genus furfuris et farragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> are the depressive, debasive denominations, whereby I. O. having first advanc'd the <hi>light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> and <hi>law of God in the heart</hi> into its proper place, prerogative, Titles, and Authority, as Gods <hi>Vicar on earth</hi> (which Office the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> have long usurped) as a faithfull witnesse, right reverend Recorder, and subordinate <hi>Judge for God,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man in the Conscience, doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Thrust</hi> it out again from its <hi>Throne, Rob</hi> it of its <hi>Recordership, detrude</hi> it from its <hi>true Title, Divest</hi> it of all its <hi>Authority, Digrade</hi> it from its <hi>Vice-gerentship,</hi> turn it down from the <hi>Bench</hi> to the <hi>Bar,</hi> and there, like a <hi>Justice</hi> of neither <hi>Peace</hi> nor <hi>Truth,</hi> pass his scornfull sentence on it, and damn it into utter <hi>darkness,</hi> among a <hi>crue of Counterfeits, fanatical fancies</hi> meer <hi>Figments,</hi> &amp; <hi>imaginations,</hi> &amp; the whole <hi>robble</hi> of such like <hi>malefactors</hi> &amp; <hi>deceivers,</hi> as any may see, who having so much skill will be at so much pains as to consult those pieces of his <hi>Latine</hi> piece, that are to that end here cited in the margent. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fx. 1. S. 5, 6. Figmentum horrendum lum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n internum omnibus commune, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>De fictitio isto sive lumine sive verbo interno et Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sto imaginario &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ex. 3. S. 11. Fanatici nostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les enthusiasmos nescio quos jactitantes lucē internā at{que} infallibilitatem inde emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentem,</hi> &amp;c. Et <hi>S. 22. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> en rescio quod, cui nihil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune est cum scripturis, tanquā Doctorem infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem sequi, et in omnibus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedire. S. 25. Lumen illud internū Res est omnino fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta at{que} commentum crasse excogitatum. S. 28. Nihil opus est ullâ revelatione per Spiritum aut lumen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum, Enthusiasmum, &amp;c. incerta periculosa inutilia ea omnia media ad cognos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum Deum at{que} volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>jus, ideo{que} rejicienda at{que} <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>standa esse quae si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulant fanatici apparet. S. 30 Omnes istas vias et modos cognitionis Dei, ac cum eo communionis, quos jactitant Fanatici, rejici ac damnari a spiritu sancto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret, presertim Angelorum colloquia revelationes alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas a verbo scripto, deinde spiritum Fanaticorū internū omnibus commune. S. 32. Ad lumen internum seu spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum internum privatum nusquam nunquam a Deo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legamur. S. 34. Enthusias<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum omne genus fallax, incertum, incertissimum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ex.</hi> 4. S. 15. <hi>Lux nictans ne{que} è tenebris perniciosissimis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergens: <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> Deo quopiam melius.</hi> S. 21. <hi>Qualitas nescio quae divina, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, verè Nihil.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:95242:24"/> Wee see then that though these men agree all together to witnesse against the <hi>Truth,</hi> yet their witnesse agrees not together within it self, their Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions assent not, but assault one the other about the self same subject, the <hi>light,</hi> some saying, as they said of Christ, <hi>he is a good man,</hi> others <hi>nay</hi> but he <hi>deceiveth the people: One while</hi> tis <hi>O divinae Originis lumen! O voo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dei effectualu! non Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem sonat, est Dea, aut a Deo certè; O Lux Dei seipsam declarans, et authoritatem suam, per quam Deus infallib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liter revelat seipsum hominibus! quid verbis opus est cum Ipsa loquitur? quid testibus ad extra ad convincendum?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O Lex Dei in corde scripta; in mentibus hominum insita! ibi loquens, judicans in Nomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Domini, Nomen Dei, per quod seipsum exhibet cognoscendum,</hi> &amp;c. Anon again, <hi>in hoc Nomine Domini incipit omne malum,</hi> Then tis, <hi>O pestis! O Labes! O nequitia! ipsa nequitia nequior.</hi> So then Sua ipsorum contra seipsos Pugna de Luce sic se habet: Ex hac parte <hi>pudor</hi> et <hi>pudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citia</hi> est, illinc <hi>petulantia</hi> et <hi>stuprum:</hi> Hinc <hi>fides</hi> est, illinc <hi>fraudatio;</hi> hinc <hi>pietas,</hi> il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linc <hi>scelus;</hi> hinc <hi>constantia,</hi> illinc <hi>furor;</hi> hinc <hi>certitudo,</hi> illinc <hi>fallibilis pretextus;</hi> hinc <hi>honestas.</hi> illinc <hi>turpitudo;</hi> hinc <hi>justa, justitia</hi> (adeo{que} si fieri possit) <hi>justitia justior;</hi> illinc <hi>ficta, fictitia, falsa, falsissima, fallaciâ ipsâ fallacior:</hi> hinc <hi>Dei</hi> quidam <hi>digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> seu insculptio quaedam in cordibus, non nisi per <hi>Dei</hi> quidem ipsius manus, illinc (<hi>Ironicè) Deus</hi> nescio quis? seu forsan <hi>Deo</hi> quopiam quid melius, aut ipso <hi>Diabolo</hi> pejus; hinc penè <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, illinc verè <hi>nihil,</hi> hinc <hi>Lux</hi> ipsa <hi>luce</hi> clarior, illinc <hi>merae Tenebrae &amp; caecitas, adeo{que} obscuritate ipsa ferè obscurior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One more <hi>Jigge</hi> of I. O. about the Light of God we testifie to, as one and the same <hi>gift</hi> or <hi>grace of God</hi> in all, as to its nature, though different in measure, is this, which is in part toucht on above, and then I leave them all to <hi>Dance</hi> in the dark all together if they will, till they are as weary, as I am in <hi>tracing</hi> after them: He may well say <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of it, yet <hi>verè nihil,</hi> for he first makes it <hi>every thing,</hi> and at last <hi>just nothing,</hi> as any one may find comparing his first <hi>Treatise</hi> with his last <hi>Tract <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Theses:</hi> One while he calls it <hi>metaphoricall,</hi> not <hi>proper;</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles <hi>proper,</hi> not <hi>metaphoricall;</hi> One while <hi>natural,</hi> as opposite to <hi>civill,</hi> and not <hi>morall, spirituall,</hi> nor <hi>supernaturall;</hi> Otherwhiles and in other respects he makes it <hi>civill, morall, spirituall,</hi> and in effect <hi>supernaturall,</hi> as in opposition to <hi>naturall;</hi> One while (<hi>Ironically</hi>) some certain <hi>divine soul</hi> of the world <hi>mixt with all things,</hi> yea all these things above said, yea <hi>all things</hi> also, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Otherwhile <hi>verè nihil,</hi> truly <hi>nothing;</hi> One while <hi>common to all</hi> and <hi>universall,</hi> but then <hi>not saving;</hi> Otherwhile <hi>sufficient</hi> and <hi>saving,</hi> but then <hi>particular</hi> only and <hi>peculiar to few,</hi> not <hi>common</hi> nor <hi>univarsall:</hi> yea the Light is made little lesse then a <hi>Monster</hi> of all shapes, a <hi>nescio quid?</hi> a <hi>certain naturall, supernaturall, civill, morall, spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, reall, metaphoricall, sufficient, insufficient, efficacious, ineffectuall, usefull, useless, safe, dangerous, peculiar, common, speciall, generall, particular, universail,</hi> Every thing, which when all comes to all is none knowes what, but a <hi>meer just No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> So here is a <hi>Ʋnity,</hi> thus parting it self into a <hi>Plurality,</hi> divided first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Duality,</hi> then turned into a <hi>Trinity,</hi> then quartered into a <hi>Quaternity,</hi> then extended into an <hi>Ʋniversality</hi> or certain <hi>Omniality,</hi> and then as some <hi>Nihil in Nil revertens,</hi> returning back into a <hi>Particularity,</hi> and narrowed up nearer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Neutrality,</hi> till it resolve and annihilate it self at last into a very <hi>Nullity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:95242:24"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus the <hi>Priest's work,</hi> who talk for <hi>Self,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is <hi>Tangling</hi> talk against it <hi>Self;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Gainst <hi>Truth</hi> a Prate, a piteous <hi>Preachment,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That can't make good its own <hi>Impeachment.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As Dr: <hi>Owens</hi> Doctrine <hi>Does,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who heeds not well which way he <hi>Goes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Baxter's, Tomb's, Dansons</hi> dances <hi>Round,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Round again in th' self same <hi>Ground;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It staggers to and fro, and <hi>Reels,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Skips up and down, and runs on <hi>Wheels,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Starts aside like some broken <hi>Bow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Crosses <hi>Christ</hi> like <hi>Cris X Crosse</hi> in th' <hi>Row,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoso can <hi>feel</hi> in it may <hi>Feel</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As 'twere a <hi>Wheel</hi> within a <hi>Wheel:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Net, Gin, Trap</hi> a Snare's in <hi>It,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Whirlpool, Gulf, Bottomlesse Pit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wind, Dust, Husk, Chaffe,</hi> no stable <hi>Steeple,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Tale,</hi> that takes unstable <hi>People,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Toy,</hi> a <hi>Cloud, Mist, Smoak,</hi> a <hi>Fogg,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No <hi>Quakerisme,</hi> but some <hi>Quavering Bogg;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Quick-sand,</hi> a <hi>Quagmire,</hi> that <hi>Sucks,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who's in 't his feet out hardly <hi>Plucks,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Himself who's <hi>In,</hi> gets <hi>seldome Out,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It self's more <hi>seldome In</hi> then <hi>Out;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It flutters like some blind night <hi>Bat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now <hi>here,</hi> now <hi>there,</hi> this way, now <hi>That,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now it is <hi>One thing,</hi> then <hi>Another,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And now and then nor t' <hi>One</hi> nor t' <hi>Other.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Somtimes</hi> it's <hi>This, somtimes</hi> it's <hi>That,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Somtimes</hi> its <hi>This,</hi> and <hi>This,</hi> and <hi>That,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Somtimes</hi> 'tis <hi>either This,</hi> or <hi>That,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Somtimes</hi> 'tis <hi>neither This,</hi> nor <hi>That,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now <hi>This,</hi> not th' <hi>Other,</hi> anon its <hi>Either,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then by and by both <hi>Both,</hi> and <hi>Neither.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One while</hi> it looks like <hi>So,</hi> not <hi>No,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Another while</hi> like <hi>No,</hi> not <hi>So,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One way</hi> it seems or <hi>So,</hi> or <hi>No,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Another way,</hi> nor <hi>No,</hi> nor <hi>So,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some wayes</hi> it shewes both <hi>So</hi> and <hi>No,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So 't's a meer endlesse <hi>No,</hi> and <hi>So.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sam: Fisher.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:95242:25"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SIc O sic</hi> Quantas, <hi>pateras{que}</hi> Quotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quas{que} Tu, plenas</hi> Babilone Totas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haud Tibi, at Sancto cuicun{que}</hi> Notas,</l>
                  <l>Bestia Potas?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scripta Scriptorum modo multa</hi> Notas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scripta Scripturae modo sacra</hi> Notas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Huic tamèn caecos oculos,</hi> Remotas</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Reddis et</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Puncta contendis, literae{que}</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Esse movendas ne{que} nec</hi> Remotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Esse nec novas, sed habere</hi> Notas</l>
                  <l>Biblia <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Esse Scripturas bene</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aut per, aut propter licet</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Esse sed mentem{que}, manus{que}</hi> Lotas</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non benè</hi> Notas.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diruis nunc quae oedificas,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <note place="margin">Si quis seu Quaerit Quare? seu Queritur Quod hîc loci non curātur vel verbō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Qualitas, vol syllabōrum Quantĭ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. Sciat dehinc nos Rusticos nec magisnec minus cū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rătŭros vel Variĕta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Verborum, vel Quantitătē nostrŏ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Syllābŏrum, Quam videmus vos Acâdĕmīcos parum Cūrăre vel Verītă<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Verbŏrum, vel Qualitǎ vostrŏ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Syllog smŏrum.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Esse, vocales, literas{que}</hi> Votas</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. am, et has meras dein' esse</hi> (O Rotas)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non it</hi> Notas.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perfici per has aliquando</hi> Votas</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Posse vel cunctos, aliquando (O</hi> Rotas)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neminem hic purum fieri</hi> Revotas</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Posse: Ita</hi> Motas.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ebriaris sic, titub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s{que}</hi> 'grotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haud dubes nunc, nunc dubitas,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>(<hi>O Sacerdos</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>modo</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quî sit</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quod scis hoc nescis, quasi in Orbe</hi> Rotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vertis Hûc, Illûc, modo circa</hi> Rotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fluctuas, curris, modo retro</hi> Rotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ʋndi{que}</hi> Rotas:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ʋs{que} dum rotas, rotulas{que}</hi> Rotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nectis in</hi> Rotis. <hi>rotătim{que}</hi> Rotas,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tota dum TENET, tŏtătim{que}</hi> Totas</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>OPERA</hi> ROTAS.</l>
               </lg>
               <list>
                  <item>ROTAS</item>
                  <item>OPERA</item>
                  <item>TENET</item>
                  <item>AREPO</item>
                  <item>SATOR</item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dixi haud magis</hi> malus Piscator, <hi>ac Tv, ac</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tui (O</hi> Sacerdos) <hi>estis</hi> pessimi Pisces, <hi>qui, ni</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Régeneremini, Rejiciemini <hi>in aeternum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In</hi> Vi, Via, Vita, Virtute <hi>ac</hi> Veritate <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini (si Salvabimini) Salvetote.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sam: Fisher.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:95242:25"/>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>